<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ordinance for tythes dismounted, from all Mosaicall, evangelicall, and true magesteriall right. By that valliant and most victorious champion, the great anti-clergy of our times, his superlative holyness, reverend young Martin Mar-Priest, sonne to old Martin the Metropolitane. Commended and presented to the petitioners of Hertford-shire, for their further encouragement, and for provocation of other counties to become petitionary with them against the unhallowed illegall exaction of tythes.</title>
            <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E313_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90244)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 51:E313[27] or 247:E313[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ordinance for tythes dismounted, from all Mosaicall, evangelicall, and true magesteriall right. By that valliant and most victorious champion, the great anti-clergy of our times, his superlative holyness, reverend young Martin Mar-Priest, sonne to old Martin the Metropolitane. Commended and presented to the petitioners of Hertford-shire, for their further encouragement, and for provocation of other counties to become petitionary with them against the unhallowed illegall exaction of tythes.</title>
                  <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Martin Claw-Clergy printer to the Reverend Assembly of Divines, for Bartholomew Bang-Priest, and are to be sold at his shop in Toleration-street, at the signe of the Subjects Liberty, right opposite to Persecution-Court,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Europe [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646. [i.e. 1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Martin Mar-Priest = Richard Overton.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false.</note>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy December 29, 1645; Wing has 1646.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 29 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Westminster Assembly (1643-1652) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113342:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113342:1"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Aſſembly of DIVINES, Aſſembled in Holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> Bleſſing and Benediction from his Superlative Holineſs, Reverend Young MARTIN MAR-PRIEST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earken with fear and reverence, unto the Words of His Holineſs, Reverend Young <hi>Martin Mar-Prieſt,</hi> as you ſhall find them written in the fourth Book of his vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sanctity, <hi>The Ordinance for Tythes diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</hi> But Beloved, the Glaſſe haſteneth, and it is not ſeaſonable now this <hi>Good Time,</hi> to detaine you too long; for I know, though out of your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Piety,</hi> you diſlike the Papall Sanctity thereof, yet cut of the Presbyterian accuteneſs of your Stomakes, you would willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate your Reverend Intrailes with the delicate belly-timber ſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities thereof; for I know, Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m-Pottage, Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d Pyes, and other ſuch toothſome toyes have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> been very naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaſing to the men of our Cloth: Wherefore, Dearly Beloved, leaſt I ſhould tranſgreſſe too much upon the ſervent Zeal of your Appitites, I ſhall leave the <hi>diviſion</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> to your ſelves, as able proficients therein, after a moſt Scholaſtick method; onely I ſhall Devote theſe my Pious Obſervations upon the Divinity of your Title of the <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Tythes,</hi> unto your moſt Sacred Protection and Peruſall, as a <hi>Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi> or paſtime for thoſe Holy-dayes, for your better concoction, not doubting, but even your ſelves will alſo ſhortly be throughly digeſted, and be caſt out as the <hi>Excrements</hi> of the Land, if you doe not put a ſwift period to your <hi>Tythe plundering Divinity:</hi> And to that end I have in ſome meaſure diſcovered the iniquity and vanity of your pretended <hi>Jure Divino</hi> to the <hi>Exaction of Tythes;</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers'd and clear'd up your myſty fogges, wherewith you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotted, corrupted and infattuated the peoples underſtandings into a blind zeal thereof; whereby (if they pleaſe) they may now ſee, that
<pb facs="tcp:113342:2"/>
the priviledge and property thereof is their owne, both by <hi>Divine</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Epiſcopall extirpation,</hi> the ever to be Honoured Petitioners of <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire,</hi> who now have <hi>broke the Ice</hi> of this grand Oppreſſion, even pluck'd at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tythes,</hi> that the reſt of the Counties may follow them, as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt the Biſhops; and the Lord ſtir them up, and give them good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that our Children after us may reap the benefit of their happy beginnings.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>(grave and Reverend</hi> ASSEMBLY,) in teſtimony that our <hi>Holyneſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>zeal</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>Dedicatory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtanding,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Holyneſſes</hi> thereat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your Cloth's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Fort,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113342:2"/>
            <head>THE ORDINANCE FOR TYTHES DISMOUNTED, From all Moſaicall, Evangelicall, and true Mageſteriall Right. <hi>OR, The Clergy utterly untitled of their JURE DIVINO, for their Exaction of</hi> TYTHES.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE AS under the late Regall and Epiſcopall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancy, the <hi>Exaction of Tythes</hi> hath for a long time been coerſively impoſed upon the People of this Kingdome, for the advance and magnificence of one ſort thereof, entitled the <hi>Clergy,</hi> who (out of their divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) have very prudently ever pretended and pleadeded their <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> thereto, to be <hi>JURE DIVINO,</hi> whereby both Mageſtrate and People have ever been perſwaded, as their duties, the one to command, the other to obey the <hi>exaction</hi> thereof, thorough
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113342:3"/>
the myſterious ſubtilty, &amp; ſpecious pretences of that <hi>Chemarim</hi> Sect, that Canniball litter of Tyth-mongring <hi>Negroes:</hi> And now that we might have a <hi>thorrough Reformation</hi> (both in and perſon, I ſhould ſay) in Church and State, under the Parliamentary and Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Authority, the ſame is very wiſely and diſcreetly continued and reconfirmed: O Reader, here with <hi>Reverend MARTIN,</hi> ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at their wit! down upon thy knees, up with thy hands, and gloor <hi>(Fresbyter-like,)</hi> with thine eyes, admiring and adoring this <hi>happy Reformation,</hi> and ſing <hi>Hallalujab</hi> for ever, and for ever, that we are bleſt with ſuch a <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Synod,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> ſuch <hi>a bomination bundance of Ordinances; Ordinances</hi> upon <hi>Ordinances,</hi> even whole <hi>Carl-loades of contradicting Ordinances, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Brethreu!</hi> to eſtabliſh ſuch a croaking gender of frisking froggy <hi>Presbyters,</hi> bred in, and skipt from the myery Bogges of Epiſcopacy, thus to inrich them with the Tenths of the Kingdome, by a more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull and obligatory Authority then before: <hi>Let all the land feare them let all the Inhabitants thereof ſtand in awe of them, for they but ſpeake, and it is done,</hi> out of their <hi>primative Zeal,</hi> they doe but claime them of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> and the godly <hi>Parliament</hi> forthwith moſt prudently inveſt their <hi>Sanctities,</hi> (to confirme <hi>as infallible</hi> the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of their <hi>Title)</hi> with a moſt juditious elaborate Act, the <hi>Hallowed Ordinance for Tythes,</hi> (O the purity of our Times!) dignify'd and enrich'd with power coercive to plunder the Goods, and impriſon the Perſons of ſuch as ſhall refuſe the paiment thereof; whereby the generallity of the people are awed, and dare not prye, or once glance into the Arke of their <hi>ſacred Title,</hi> leaſt they be ſmit with a <hi>Confiſcation,</hi> &amp;c. that the <hi>Divinity</hi> of their <hi>Title</hi> goes now as currant for <hi>Tith-ware</hi> amongſt the vulgarity, as if it had the Goſpel-Image and Superſcription upon it, that now the ſilly ſoules, even in the middeſt of their millitary taxations, <hi>Iſſacbar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> like, humbly couch under the burthen of their <hi>Exaction,</hi> when as indeed, in equity they had more need to ſubſtract then to adde, to ſhake off, rather then to contract an unneceſſary Burthen to their over-burthened ſhoulders: But the <hi>Presbyters</hi> doe not greatly care, conſidering the <hi>breadth of their backs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore out of duty unto God, and love unto my Country in this time of publick neceſſity; I ſhall, as neere as I can, diſcover the vanity of their <hi>Title,</hi> that the oppreſſed may ſee it, and ſomething
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113342:3"/>
caſe themſelves of their Burthen. But that I may the better evince it to every rationall and ordinary capacity, and ſtop the mouth of the moſt materiall oppoſition, I ſhall make triall of their <hi>divine Title</hi> in their moſt fundamentall pretences; which may naturally be digeſted into their deductions from three heads, to wit, <hi>Moſaicall, Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and ſo anſwerable reduce my matter into three Sections.</p>
               <p>For on theſe 3. Pillars the Clergy would erect the cock-loft of their <hi>Jure Divine,</hi> even from thence hold and maintaine their <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuce</hi> of <hi>Divine Right</hi> unto the exaction of <hi>Tythes;</hi> but I ſhall impac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially examine the divinity of their Title deducted from theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Heads, as being the moſt rationall and ſatisfactory way of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to lay the Axe unto the root of the Tree, to unbottome their building; for if I pluck from them their <hi>main Pillars,</hi> their Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall props, downe tumbles the great Goddeſſe, <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, Prieſts, Tythe-pigges, Pullen and all; and what a fray then there will be, judge yee. And firſt concerning the Authority of their <hi>Moſaicall Title.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="sect">
               <head>SECTION I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Clergies Moſaicall Title of <hi>Jure Divino</hi> unto the exaction of TYTHES.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat wee may the better make tryall hereof, it is to be conſidered, that the Clergy of this Kingdome doe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochially Officiate therein as the Miniſters of JESUS CHRIST <hi>(as they pretend themſelves to be)</hi> and yet for their Miniſtery require the tenth of all our Subſtance, by vertue of a <hi>Moſaicall Authority,</hi> the which how in equity they can doe, in caſe they ſhould be ſuch, they muſt evidence how Goſpel Ordinances, ſuch as are proper to the Church of Chriſt, are to be practiſed, and to receive their authority from a <hi>Moſaicall</hi> Inſtitution? If they may not, that is, if nothing can give priviledge or right to an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113342:4"/>
property, but an <hi>Evangelicall Authority;</hi> then why doe you for your Miniſtery of the Goſpel (as you would make us beleeve it is) impoſe upon us the bondage of a <hi>Moſaicall Inſtitution,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Exaction of Tythes,</hi> whoſe Authority, Inſtitution and Beeing was from the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and therein for that ſervice terminated for the Miniſters of his Houſe?</p>
               <p>If they be to be practiſed from <hi>Moſaicall Inſtitutions;</hi> then, Is not that to make the <hi>Goſpel of none effect,</hi> of leſſe authority then the Law, and ſo CHRIST interiour to <hi>Moſes;</hi> his Ordinances inſufficient, and not binding, himſelf neceſſitated to be benolden to <hi>Moſes</hi> for Authority to ſtrengthen his <hi>Inſtitutions, Ordinances, &amp;c.</hi> and to make them obligatory, undervalue his Mediatorſhip, make himſelf inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for a <hi>Saviour?</hi> for ſhould he not have Authority of himſelf for his own Inſtitutions, Ordinances, &amp;c. then would hee be farre leſſe ſufficient to be the <hi>Redeemer of the World;</hi> for the worke of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, Salvation, &amp;c.</hi> is of greater Power, then to make a Law Obligatory, for if he be not able for the leſſe, it is impoſſible hee ſhould doe the greater: And ſo this is no other, then to denie his MEDIATOURSHIP, his <hi>Redemption,</hi> the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore to practiſe <hi>Evangelicall Ordinances,</hi> to build the Houſe of Chriſt with the mouldred rubbidge and ruines of the Law, to inveſt Chriſts Miniſters, with a bare <hi>Moſaicall Authority,</hi> to claime an <hi>Evangelicall Title</hi> from a <hi>Judaicall Inſtitution,</hi> to take <hi>Tythes</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> by vertue of <hi>Moſes his Commiſsion,</hi> cannot poſſibly be without thoſe horrible abſurdities, deſtructive to all Religion and Morallity.</p>
               <p>Wherefore <hi>(ventrable Brethren,)</hi> you muſt, if you will have ſuch a manner of Maintenance to be yours of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> prove your Authority from the <hi>Commiſſion of Chriſt,</hi> have a <hi>Goſpel Ordinance</hi> for it: but let me tell you by the way, when you have done that, to wit, <hi>proved the exaction of Tythes from the Goſpel, for the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> yet it remaineth for you, <hi>to prove your ſelves to be ſuch Miniſters,</hi> or elſe wee ſhall neither eſteem you for the one, or give you the other; for if of <hi>Evangelicall Right</hi> they be due, and the men of your cloth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113342:4"/>
the Perſons to whom they are due; then from an <hi>Evangelicall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> you muſt prove both the one and the other, your ſelves the very men, and this that you require, to be the ſame that CHRIST allotteth his Servants, for their Miniſteriall, Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Function: For if He be your WORK-MASTER, and you doe His WORKE, all Authority being His, and onely deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative from him, He muſt ſet the Wages, and the wages hee ſetteth, you muſt there with only be contented: If you doe the WORKE, you muſt have the Wages of the WORKE, otherwiſe not: if his Wages doe not content you, then you are none of His <hi>Servants; for you are his ſervants whoſe wages you receive; and if you receive</hi> Moſes <hi>his Wages, then you are</hi> Moſes <hi>his ſervants, and ſo muſt doe his</hi> WORKE, <hi>as offer Sacrifice and the like, which were to repaire and rear up the</hi> Partition Wall <hi>againe, which</hi> CHRIST <hi>hath broake downe betwixt</hi> JEW and GENTILE, <hi>to denie him come in the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>(Reverend Brethren,)</hi> you muſt not thinke to doe CHRIST'S WORKE, and exact <hi>Moſes</hi> his Wages; if out of your Piety you thinke good of the Worke; out of your honeſty you muſt be content with the Wages belonging to the Worke.</p>
               <p>And truly <hi>(Pious Sirs,)</hi> till ſuch time as you give us an expreſſe Commandement out of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> for this Legall, Levitticall exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Tythes,</hi> for your ſervice, which you pretend is the Service of the Goſpel, till then wee ſhall be bold to forbeare the paiment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but no ſooner ſhall you have proved your ſelves the Miniſters of the Goſpel, from a Goſpel Authority, and <hi>Tythes</hi> the wages of the Goſpel, from a Goſpel Ordinance, and your ſervice which you performe, to be the ſervice for which ſuch wages is allowed by the Goſpel; I ſay, no ſooner ſhall you make theſe 3. appeare, but I ſhall yeeld you your Right, grant your Title to be <hi>Jure Divine,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all my Independant <hi>Brethren</hi> to doe the like to the men of your Order; Then will wee pay you your A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, fill your Barnes with Tyth-Cocks, both of Hay, and all manner of graine, enrich you with Heards of Tyth-Pigges, focks of Lambes, of Chickens, Geeſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113342:5"/>
Then will wee make a Presbyter as glorious, as Pontificall; yea, feed him as fat as a Biſhop: Her's newes for the men of your cloath; goe, proclame a yeere of Jubilee, get an Ordinance for it, or at leaſt ſome directions from both Houſes to keep their Worſhips in action; for you know their Hiſtoricall Directions are myſticall Ordinances, witneſſe their late Directions for their Congregationall, Claſſicall, Provinciall and Nationall High Commiſſion-Courts, which at their comming out were under the notion of Directions, to feel the pulſe and temper of the people, to try whether either they could beare them, or were afraid to reject them, and now finding them either groſly ignorant, careleſſe, or elſe cowardly and degenerate, that they neither doe nor dare oppoſe them, though it be to enſlive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Poſterity in a worſe then an Arbitrary, Regall, or Epiſcopall ſervitude, to wit, in endles ſuites and appeales from Court unto Court; hereupon, they are concluded in that moſt Religious and ſpirituall Ordinance for the <hi>Supper,</hi> as abſolute Ordinances, as unalterable as the <hi>Directory;</hi> for indeed, at the firſt onſet, it was not policy, to ruſh ſuch a diabollicall and villanous invention point blanck upon us, with an, <hi>It is Decreed and Ordained by the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parliament.</hi> But after a more my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious manner of Ordination, ſlily intrude it upon us unawares in the godly and ſpecious vizor of <hi>Rules and Directions,</hi> as if our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Parliament-men had ſuch a ſpirituall and holy care over us, to give us ſuch wholſome and Pious <hi>Directions,</hi> while indeed under this innocent apparition, in the ſhape of Lambs, they are no other then ravening Wolves, rending and tearing us in pieces, for did they not pretend the ſpiritual welfare of the Kingdom in thoſe <hi>Directions,</hi> ſeem to give them, out of a godly care and pious Providence over us, for our future ſpirituall Peace and well-beeing, but what they are, let all the people judge; let them conſider whether there can be the leaſt dramme of honeſty or Religion in them, or of reſpect to the Liberty of this free-borne Nation therein, ſeeing they lay upon us a heavier yoake then ever was laid upon us in the dayes of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Now we ſhall be ſo intangled and enthrall'd in endleſſe fultes and Controverſies from Court unto Court, that if wee once fall into the all-ravenous pawes of thoſe ſpirituall Courtiers, wee muſt ſcarce expect to finiſh a ſuit in 7. yeeres; and what cheating and cozening, what pilling and polling, raking and exacting of fees will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113342:5"/>
there be amongſt the ſeverall Officers of thoſe ſeverall Courts, every ordinary capacity is able to judge of; it will be the greateſt thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and bondage that ever the Kingdome was involved into, and by this Ordinance of the <hi>Supper,</hi> I am afraid we ſhall all goe Supper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to bed, for there are ſuch baits and entanglements laid for the people, to catch and intrap them, as multitudes muſt needs daily fall into their hands, and when they are fallen into the ravenous jawes of this <hi>Hydra-headed High-Commiſſion,</hi> they muſt needs be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, there is no way to helpe themſelves: if they be offended, at the <hi>Congregationall High-Commiſſion;</hi> they may appeale to the <hi>Claſſicall High-Commiſſion,</hi> if they cannot be righted there, then to appeale to the <hi>Provinciall High-Commiſſion,</hi> and from the <hi>Provinciall</hi> to the <hi>Nationall High-Commiſſion,</hi> and from thence forſooth, if wee can finde no Juſtice in our tedious expenſive traverſe through theſe <hi>Spirituall</hi> HIGH-PLACES, after wee have trudg'd from <hi>High-Commiſſion</hi> to <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> removed our ſuits from Court unto Court, been at vaſt and unreaſonable expenſes in Fees from Officer to Officer, we may appeale (forſooth) to our GODS them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the PARLIAMENT <hi>(life-Ever-laſting, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, AMEN.)</hi> Of whom, how may wee expect Morcy or Juſtice then, that thus before-hand <hi>whip as with the ſtings of Scorpions, and grinde us betwen the devouring</hi> JAWES <hi>of ſuch deviliſh Tyrannicall Courts, which will even cruſh our bones in pieces, and ſqueeſe out our very marrow and juice, ſuck out our very hearts-blood, like ſo many greedy ſalvage Canniballs, and devouer our fleſh, and ſwallow it down into the filthy conſuming panches of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous blood-thirſty Clergy:</hi> For what Eccleſiaſticall Court ever was there in any Nation of the World, managed by the Clergy, which was not improved to wicked, bloody and Tyrannicall ends? Have they not proved (where ever they have been) the moſt inſufferable burthen and bondage the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> ever ſuſtained, or groaned under; the moſt deſtructive to the <hi>Peoples Liberty, Peace, and well-being?</hi> Conſider but the <hi>Spanniſh Inquiſition,</hi> and our late <hi>High-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> of what deſperate and deſtructive conſequence they have been to the Peoples weal, which after long proceſſe of time proved ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable to the people, that they have, and daily ſpend their lives and fortunes to free them and their Poſterities from ſuch ſpirituall ſlavery, and uſurpation of their Liberties, which they ſo long had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113342:6"/>
ſuſtained by ſuch Eccleſiaſticall <hi>Courts,</hi> which very <hi>Courts</hi> were Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and put downe, as Tyrannicall and deſtructive to a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> by this very <hi>Parliament,</hi> which thus would intrude upon us far more and worſe then ever we had, or heard of before: It ſeems when our old Fathers the Biſhops grew decreped and unable, ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and gaſping for life, their young, briske and ſpermatick Sonnes the <hi>Presbyters</hi> committed inceſt with their old Beldam Mother <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> and after her long <hi>Synodean</hi> travell, by the skilfull ſubtill powerfull hand of a <hi>Parliamentary Midwife,</hi> is delivered of a litter of ugly Kubbs, every one more barbarous, cruell, bloody and Tyrannicall then their Mother: For the Kingdom muſt be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into ſeverall <hi>Provinces</hi> (not <hi>Dioceſſes</hi> forſooth, that's an Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall terme,) and every Pariſh throughout all the Provinces in the whole Kingdom muſt have a bloody <hi>Inquiſition Court</hi> founded in it, which <hi>High-Commiſsion-</hi>like ſhall have power to give and examine upon Oath, and ſuch and ſuch Pariſhes in each Province ſhall make a Claſſis, ſo that in one Province ſhall be ſeverall Claſſes, and every Claſſis ſhall be conſtituted and founded into another <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> which ſhall have Power over ſo many particular Pariſhes of ſuch a Province, and over that <hi>Claſsicall Inquiſition,</hi> there muſt be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and over the <hi>Provinciall</hi> there muſt be a Nation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Inquiſition:</hi> Here's like to be <hi>Inquiſition</hi> after <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> worſe then the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> after the blood of the people; wee thought our ſelves at the worſt when we knew none but the <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> but what ſhall we thinke now, that are like to be ten thouſand times worſe?</p>
               <p>The Biſhops Courts ſtript us of our clothes, but the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Courts will ſtrip us of coates, skinnes, lives and all, for any thing that I can diſcerne; For how have theſe men, before they be inveſted with this Power, before theſe Courts be ſetled, both in their Writings and Preachings ſuggeſted, ſollicited and moved the Parliament to out off the contrary-minded to them; <hi>Byfeild</hi> in his Sermon, <hi>deſired that their Houſes might be pull'd downe, and Gibbets made of the Timber to bang them,</hi> and to that end all of them have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to get this <hi>bloody Power</hi> into their hands, to that end that they might perſecute them from Court to Court, even unto death, for if they meant freindly towards them, they would never endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113342:6"/>
after ſuch Courts <hi>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not to confound them with cruelty, they never intend to deale with them by love; but by Power and Violence, but what kinde of ſucceſſe this Kingdome and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may expect thereby, they may eaſily diſcerne, if they reflect but their eyes upon the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>full Iſſues of our former Eccleſiaſticall Courts, and for better ſucceſſe by them, I dare be bold to Propheſie they ſhall never obtaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to returne from this too tedious digreſſion, to our matter, or preſent Controverſie in hand, be pleaſed <hi>(Venerable Brethren,)</hi> to conſider, that if you will have <hi>Tythes</hi> ſtill to remaine, and to be yours of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> from a <hi>Moſaicall Authority,</hi> then you moſt be the Perſons to whom <hi>Tythes were commanded to be paid,</hi> for they were nor could be of <hi>Divine Right</hi> due to none other, then ſuch to whom they were commanded to be paid, for it is the command of God that gives a <hi>Divine Right</hi> unto a thing commanded; Put they were commanded to be paid to the <hi>Levites</hi> for their ſervice; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if for your <hi>Miniſteriall Function</hi> you will have the <hi>Levites wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> then you muſt every man of you prove your ſelves lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the loynes of <hi>Levi,</hi> and ſo none but ſuch that are of that Tribe, to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, and <hi>Tythes</hi> to be paid to none other: Therefore till you ſhew us a perfect Geneallogie of your deſcent legitimately from the loynes of <hi>Levi,</hi> wee ſhall not give you <hi>the Wages of the ſonnes of Levi:</hi> Goe ſearch your <hi>Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> turne over your numerous Volumes; you may finde it cock-ſure amongſt ſome of the Old <hi>Fathers,</hi> for they afford matter for all your neceſſities.</p>
               <p>2. Theſe <hi>Tenths</hi> were ordained to be of the encreaſe of the Eleven <hi>Tribes,</hi> from their ſeverall portions in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and not of other nations of people: Therefore if you will have the <hi>Levites Portion,</hi> you muſt goe to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and receive it of the <hi>Eleven Tribes,</hi> or elſe you muſt prove <hi>England</hi> to be <hi>Canaan,</hi> your ſelves the <hi>Levites,</hi> and us the <hi>Eleven Tribes,</hi> which for Univerſity men, ſuch exact <hi>Logitions</hi> as your ſelves, is nothing to doe, goe ſophiſticate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into a <hi>Syllogiſme,</hi> and you need not doubt of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> as infallible as the Empyrick's <hi>Proba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſt:</hi> in the meane time, wee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lay up your <hi>Tythes</hi> for you, and gather them very ſafe into one Barnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113342:7"/>
Methinks <hi>(Right venerable</hi> BRETHREN,) you have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great over-ſight of late, to ſuffer your Journey-men <hi>The two Houſes of</hi> PARLIAMENT, to put out ſuch inconſiderate <hi>Directions</hi> for the <hi>Diviſion of the Kingdome into Provinces, Claſſes, &amp;c.</hi> and not to paralell them (conſidering it's a time of ſetling this <hi>Levittio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Order)</hi> with the diviſion of the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> had you but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with MARTIN, and made him your <hi>Directory</hi> Journey-man, he would have reduced the people into <hi>Twelve Tribes,</hi> divided the Kingdome into <hi>anſwerable Portions;</hi> and your ſelves then might eaſily have proved your lineall legitimate deſcent from the Loynes of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi,</hi> for it had been nothing then from thence to have drawne an <hi>Argument</hi> as good as an ORDINANCE <hi>of the Lords and Commons for the true payment of</hi> TYTHES, or the like; but to returne to our matter.</p>
               <p>Beloved <hi>Brethren,</hi> I would have you conſider, that the very <hi>Jewes</hi> themſelves to this day have determined the <hi>equity</hi> of their <hi>Tythes</hi> to their owne Land, for their Doctors conclude, that regularly no Inhabitants but of the Land of Iſrael were to pay any, and even to this day by their Law, (being deſperſed and ſojourning in ſtrange lands;) no <hi>Tythes</hi> of their encreaſe in ſuch Lands, is either paid, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or held equall amongſt themſelves to be paid; yea, by their Law, they are to pay none. And thoſe that live in the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> now, pay none for want of their Temple and PRIESTHOOD, for their ſecond Temple no ſooner was deſtroyed, but with it their Law of <hi>Firſt-fruits, Therumah,</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> ceaſed, and thoſe that live diſperſed, pay none, both for want of their Temple, &amp;c. as alſo for the reſtrainment thereof to the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> but you are neither <hi>Jewes, Levites, in the land of</hi> Canaan, <hi>have the Temple Prieſthood,</hi> or any thing appartaining thereto, and yet you require them by that Law, and claime them of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> no commandement or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right</hi> being given to any other but the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> to receive them, therefore how equall your claime is, let thoſe that pay them judge: for if they themſelves, that had the commandment yeeld up for thoſe conſiderations, their right and equity in them, and may not of <hi>Divine Right</hi> require them, much leſſe may you that are neither JEWES, LEVITES, or ever had a Commandement from God for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113342:7"/>
3. If you were <hi>Levites,</hi> yet were it unreaſonable and unjuſt for you to exact above the <hi>Levites</hi> portion, a Levitticall right is bounded preciſely within a Levitti call Compaſſe; if you will be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Levites for your Divine Title, you muſt be numbred with them in the nature of their revenue, and thereto preciſely confined, and if of their Order for their revenue, then muſt you not diſdaine to be ranked in the nnmber whereto that Revenue was ordained, and be content with the allowance that ſhall come to your ſhare from that Ordination, now the Levites for their maintenance were rancked amongſt <hi>the Fatherleſse, Widdowes and Strangers, Deutr.</hi> 14. 29. and 26. 12.</p>
               <p>Such therefore muſt be your Companions, (thinke it no diſparagement to your cloath,) and you muſt be content with your diviſion, and with what falls to your ſhare; The <hi>Fatherleſse,</hi> the <hi>Widdow, ſtranger, &amp;c.</hi> was to have a ſhare, and ſubſiſtance, to eat and to be ſatisfyed out of the <hi>Tythe,</hi> as well as the Levite, therefore for the Levite to exact all the <hi>Tythes,</hi> were to eat the bread out of the mouthes of the <hi>Fatherleſse,</hi> the <hi>Widdows,</hi> and the <hi>Sran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So then, the encroaching and uſurping the whole <hi>Tenthes,</hi> yea, all things conſidered, even the ſixth or ſeventh part of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into the hands of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> under this Levitticall pretence, is no other then ſuch oprreſſion to the <hi>Fatherleſſe, Widdow,</hi> &amp;c. But wee ſee our Clergie under this pretence exact all, and more then the Tenthes, and ſpend it all upon themſelves, and turne <hi>the Fatherleſse, the Widdow and the Stranger,</hi> to the wide world; and though every Pariſh thus largely give their Almes for the generall ſupply of the poore, theſe men get all into their hands, and cauſe the <hi>Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse</hi> to goe naked without clothing, <hi>and they take away the ſheafe from the hungery.</hi> Job 24. 10. but cloath themſelves in coſtly array, feed on dainties, live at eaſe, and take their pleaſure, that they are more like Lords then Almes-men; while the other Almes-people, <hi>the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse, Widdow, &amp;c.</hi> are ready to periſh for food, cloathed in ragges, and forc'd to begge, and would periſh quite, ſhould not the Pariſh take further compaſſion over them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113342:8"/>
Therefore MARTIN would adviſe the Fatherleſſe, the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the Stranger, ſince this <hi>Levitticall</hi> Order of <hi>Tything</hi> muſt ſtill be retained on foot, to come in and claime their right, for if the <hi>Inheritance</hi> muſt be granted, the <hi>Inheritances</hi> muſt be thereto en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled; ſo long as the <hi>Poſſeſsion</hi> endureth, ſo long their Intereſt does continue; as long as they will have the one, ſo long they muſt grant the other: and let not thoſe greedy <hi>Cormorants</hi> devour up their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there may be a more competent anſwerable equallity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe <hi>Almes People,</hi> the <hi>Levite, the Fatherleſſe, the Widdow and the Stranger; that all may have a competency, the Fatherleſſe, Widow and Stranger, as well as the</hi> Levite; <hi>that this rich and fruitfall Nation may not longer be branded with the infamy of ſuch multitudes of Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſuch miſerable forlorne Objects of Compaſsions, left deſtitute in a Land where there is ſuch a redundancy of Proviſion; for were the</hi> Tythes, <hi>which are a vaſt, and almoſt unvaluable wealth, but proportionably di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided amongſt the Poore throughtout every Pariſh in the Kingdome, all would have ſufficient, and none would want; only our proud frisking Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites would be a little abated in their Pride; Their great Buttons would no more neatly faſhion forth their ſhoulders, then the loops their necks: their Wives would ſcarſe have Fannes to coole their beauites, or ſuch like pretty toyes to humour their amorous nicer-</hi>fancies <hi>with, which trivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls way very well be ſpar'd, better then ſuffer the Fatherleſſe to goe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſy; tatter'd and torne, begge, and ready to periſh in the ſtreets: for it is a moſt unreaſonable wicked unconſcionable thing, that one ſort of Almes-men, which would be counted</hi> (forſooth) <hi>the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould devoure up the reſt, or that any ſort ſhould be richer then their Almes-Maſters; for there is above a Thouſand Lay-perſons (as they call them,) men, women and Children to one Clery-man throughout the Kingdome; in ſome Pariſhes here are above ten thouſand to one, and yet this handfull of Venerable vermine muſt have the Tenth of the encreaſe of the whole Kingdome, beſides their</hi> Gleah-land, Oblations, <hi>&amp;c. Which betrayes their unſatiable Coveſouſneſſe to take it, and the groſſe ſimplicity of the People to give it, their Bene factors muſt be glad of brown bread and Pottage to feed their hungry bellies, of leather Jackets or any thing to cover their nakedneſs, and rejoyce and bleſse God they can have it by their ſore travell and pains, by their induſtry and ſweat of their browes; they muſt cap and congue, and theſe Almes-men, this Leviticall Clergy,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113342:8"/>
deport themſelves, and live like Lords in Pompe, Honour and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; for who more honoured, who more ſtately, proud, or delitious then they?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh, MARTIN cannot forget the Germane Proverbe,</hi> The covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Prieſts, and the Mercy of God endure for ever.</p>
               <p>But that we may the more cleerly diſcover their deceit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they have bewitched the people under this <hi>Levittical Pretence,</hi> let us a little further deſcant upon <hi>the Right of the Levite,</hi> that every ordinary capacity may receive more full and ample ſatisfaction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the equity of their <hi>claine,</hi> and that thoſe counterfeit <hi>Levites, (our preſent Presbyters,) may cover their heads, and hide their faces for ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for out further inquiſition therein, and inquiry thereof, let us conſider, that though the <hi>Sonnes of Levi</hi> had a commandement to receive <hi>Tythes of the People, according to the Law, Heb.</hi> 7. 5. and though that commandement was onely for the <hi>Levites,</hi> ſo that neither any other was to receive them from the People, <hi>but the Levites,</hi> nor the people to pay them to any other, <hi>but to the Levites according to tho Law,</hi> which both did deſigne their Tythes, and bind them to their payment, yet could their ſervice for this rich Prerogative, this large Revenue, bring no perfection: All Offerings, Sacrifices and Services unto God for <hi>the ſinnes of the People,</hi> was committed to that Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and adminiſtred by them, and yet as touching the Conſcience, could not purify, or ever take away ſinnes; therefore there was a neceſſity that one of another Tribe, that ſhould not be called after the <hi>Order of Aaron</hi> ſhould ariſe, otherwiſe there could never have been Salvation, <hi>for it could not be by any thing that did at could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, or was adminiſtred by the Tribe of</hi> Levi, <hi>ſon could it, what further need was there that another Prieſt ſhould ariſe,</hi> Heb. 7. 11. <hi>therefore the Prieſthood, and commandement there of was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>lled for the weakneſſe and unprofitableneſse thereof,</hi> verſſ. 8. <hi>and been of whom better things were ſpoken, forgiveneſse of ſinnes, and eternall life, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>eth of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tribe, of whom no man gave attendance at the Altar, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the</hi> Tribe of Judah, <hi>of which</hi> Moſes <hi>ſpake nothing concerning the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood;</hi> No, not ſo much as of a <hi>Tyth-pigge,</hi> verſ. 13, 14, <hi>(a that thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Man being come, the Prieſthood changeth, and that changing, there is made of neceſsity, a change alſo of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113342:9"/>
Theſe things premiſed, the <hi>Levites</hi> therfore themſelves have no longer Authority or <hi>Divine Right</hi> unto <hi>Tysbes,</hi> according to the Law, a period being put to their Office, their Prieſt-hood ceaſing, and the Law according to which they received the wages of their Prieſthood ceaſing, neither are the people longer bound to pay them by vertue of that command, ſeeing both the Law which bound them to it, and the Preiſthood for which it was, are both diſannulled, abrogated, and ceaſed quite, and a more excellent Miniſtery obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, eſtabliſhed upon better Promiſes, by one of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake nothing of that Prieſthood, ſo that he being of another <hi>Order,</hi> and of another Tribe, being Mediatour of a better Covenant, eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon better Promiſes, neither Service, nor any thing which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to that Tribe, according to the Law, where of <hi>Tythes</hi> was one, can be tranſplanted and grafted into that Stock under deſtruction thereof, for if we will have it to beare the fruit of the Levitticall Prieſthood, wee cannot be made perfect, receiving the Promiſe of <hi>Eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore to aſcribe that which belonged to the Levitticall Prieſthood, to the Miniſtery of our Lord, which ſprang from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> is to introduce and recall the Legall Sacrifices and Services, to denie Chriſt, deſtroy his Genealogie, and diſannull his <hi>Covenant;</hi> for whatſoever appartained to the Prieſthood, was proper and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> ſo that whoſoever did officiate therein, or receive any thing belonging to the Office, was one of that Tribe, therefore to aſcribe <hi>Tythes</hi> to this <hi>Order,</hi> whereof Chriſt is, is to make him of the Tribe and Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſo deſtroyes his Mediatourſhip, and denyes ſalvation by him, for of his Order <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſpake nothing concerning the Prieſthood, now <hi>Tythes</hi> belonged and was ordained to the Prieſthood, (which Prieſt-hood was not able to cleanſe the Conſcience from ſinne, and ſo not ſufficient for ſalvation) therefore not at all doe they belong unto his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or Mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tery ariſing from another Tribe, from whence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>forgiveneſse of ſinnes, and eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. If you will have Tythes, you muſt have it of your owne bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for verily, they that were of the Sonnes of <hi>Levi,</hi> who receive the Office of the Prieſthood, have a Commandement to take <hi>Tythes</hi> of the people, according to the Law, that is <hi>of their brethren, &amp;c.</hi> Heb.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113342:9"/>
7. 5. Wherefore we of the Independant Congregations, being not of your Members, and ſo none of your brethren, you have not any authority to demand or receive them of us, the flock which you feed (if you feed any) <hi>is the ſtock of whoſe milke you muſt eat.</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 7. Now we being not of your ſtock, you muſt not thinke to eat of our milke, but you muſt be content with the milke of your owne flock: when you are our Paſtors, and wee your ſheep, you ſhall have the <hi>Tyth</hi> of our Milke, but in the meane time, MARTIN would adviſe you to be content with your owne.</p>
               <p>5. If you denie to receive <hi>Tythes</hi> as <hi>Levites,</hi> and claime them as you are Prieſts, then you muſt have no other then what was due to the Prieſts, and in <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 3. &amp;c. it is ſaid, <hi>and this ſhall be the Prieſts due, from the People, from them that offer a Sacrifice, whether it be Oxe or Sheep, and they ſhall give unto the Prieſt the ſhoulder, and the two cheeks, and the maw &amp;c.</hi> and truly, when MARTIN doth offer an Oxe or a Sheep, hee will freely give you the ſhoulder, the two Cheeks and the Maw, and hee cares not greatly, if you thinke that Oxe-cheekes are too courſe Diet, for the Prieſts of our dayes, to gratify your dainty diviner Pallates, with the great Bagge, with all its venerable appurtenances. But though this were the Prieſts due, yet for this were they to ſtay the Offering, a worke too burcherly for Preiſts now adayes; yea, they were, if there were any warre in the I and, to goe againſt the enemy, <hi>and blow an alaram with their Trumpets,</hi> and this was an Ordinance for ever amongſt the Prieſts, <hi>throughout their Generations, and they ſhall be ſaved from their enemies,</hi> Numb 10. 8, 9. Therefore if you will have our Oxe-cheeks, our Oxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mawes, you muſt all turne Trumpetters now there is warre in the Land, and ſound an <hi>Allarme;</hi> If you be Prieſts, you have not done well to forbeare all this while, for the Text ſaith, <hi>Yee ſhall be ſaved from your enemies.</hi> O Pious and Venerable Brethren, for ſo I am em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened to ſtyle you; I beſeech you be encouraged, and ſtirre up one another to this good <hi>Worke,</hi> if you be Prieſts, <hi>ſound an allarme,</hi> that wee may be ſaved from the Cavaliers, and then you ſhall have all our Oxe-cheekes, our Oxe-mawes, Bagges and Baggage; for wee are weary of the warres.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113342:10"/>
Further, if you claime them as Prieſts, then are you to require none of the People, for the <hi>Laitie</hi> paid only <hi>Firſt-fruits,</hi> not <hi>Tythes</hi> immediately to the Prieſts, but <hi>one by to the Levites, Singers, and other ſuch Miniſters: And the Levites paid the Tythe of their Tythe to the Prieſts,</hi> Numb. 18. 26. 28. <hi>Who ſo thorough the Levites, received</hi> Tyths <hi>from the Poſseſsions of the</hi> Laiety, <hi>for the Poſterity of</hi> Aaron, <hi>that had the Prieſthood, received none from the people immediately, but mediately from the bond of the</hi> Levite, <hi>and that was but a</hi> Tythe <hi>of then</hi> Tythe.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if you will be Prieſts, (as you all ſtand Prieſts by your <hi>Epiſcopall Ordination,</hi> witneſſe the late Ordinance <hi>for the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> where it is granted,) then all the Tythe that you can any wayes exact, is <hi>but the Tythe of the Tythe,</hi> the reſt, <hi>as firſt-fruits</hi> and the like, were left unto <hi>the good will of the People,</hi> for ſeeing you will be the Prieſts ſucceſſors for their maintenance, but not for their Worke, being more lazie in your generation; I tell you, though your ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were good, yet could you be hereditary to nothing then where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe Prieſts had a right; their patterne can extend no further then their own priviledge, though you and your Fathers have ſet it upon the Tentures, and ſtreetch'd it unto the portion of the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Fatherleſſe,</hi> the <hi>Widow,</hi> and the <hi>Stranger,</hi> and haye rack'd and ſcrap'd all into your Compaſſe.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Firſt-fruits</hi> of the forwardeſt were offered to the Prieſts in Eares of Wheat and Barly, Grapes, Figges, Olives, Pomegranats and Dates, and of theſe the <hi>Firſt-fruits</hi> were paid, in what quantity the owner would, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 19. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. 12. likewiſe their <hi>Theru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</hi> or <hi>Heave-Offering,</hi> or <hi>Firſt-Fruits</hi> of Wine, Oyle, Fleece, and the like, were alſo given to the Prieſts; <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 4. but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by <hi>Moſes</hi> of what Quantity: therefore from their example, you cannot tye as to the tenth of thoſe things, but though you were ſuch Prieſts, yet muſt you be content with ſuch as wee out of our own freedom ſhall give you thereof. Indeed wee read in <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> 45. 13 that the <hi>Their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or <hi>Oblation, was the ſixt part of an Ephath of an Homer of Where, and the like of Barly, and an Homer, which was alone with a Both, was neer our common Bufbell, &amp;. on Epth was the tenth part of an Homer.</hi> V. II. So that all the <hi>Obligation</hi> for this or that quantitie, that you can impoſe upon us, is at the moſt, but what <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiell</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113342:10"/>
deſcribeth, and that was but <hi>the ſixtyeth part of an Homer, which after our account, is the ſixtyeth part of a Buſbell of Wheate or Barly, for the Ephah was but the tenth part of the Buſhell, and but the ſixt part of the Tenth was to be offered: ſo that, if the confining of us to this indifferent portion will not content you,</hi> you muſt even be contented <hi>with the good will of the VULGAR, that Clergy Bugg-bare,</hi> for there is no preſident from any command for any more; or can wee read that <hi>Moſes</hi> his Prieſts ever exacted more; or indeed that they ever exicted any quantity, but wholly left it to the <hi>diſpoſition of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> which, if compared with our Prieſts, their practiſe will be found much derregatory thereto; for though they have no right at all to the ſixtyeth part, or indeed to any ſuch <hi>voluntary Offerings</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not the perſons to whom the benefit of <hi>Church-contributions</hi> were ordained) yet ſuch is their <hi>Avarice,</hi> that though they plead for the due of the <hi>Moſoicall Prieſts,</hi> yet that will not content them; for neither will they ſtand to the good will of the People, as <hi>Moſes his Prieſts</hi> did, nor yet be content with <hi>the ſixtyeth part,</hi> as they were, but they will have the <hi>Tenth;</hi> yea, above the <hi>Tenth,</hi> and that by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, whether the People will or no: therefore let the people judge of their greedyneſſe, of their jugling and deceit, who under the pretence of a thing whereto they have no right, require not only the thing it ſelf, to wit, the <hi>ſixtyeth part,</hi> but even fifty times more, and that by compulſion.</p>
               <p>6. The Officers of the <hi>Miniſtery of the Goſpel,</hi> are to be choſen by the members thereof out from amongſt themſelves, and their Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is not (as under the Law) confin'd to this or that <hi>Tribe,</hi> this or that Generation, but is generall to any Tribe or Generation whatſoever; and ſo as the ſervice is ceaſed, the perſons officiating are ceaſed, and both ceaſing, the wages muſt needs ceaſe, neither worke for which, nor perſons to whom, according to the Law, remaining: But notwithſtanding this aboliſhment, hither you fly to conſecrate your Ordinance for <hi>Tythes,</hi> with a <hi>jure Divino,</hi> as if with work-men and worke, the wages were not vaniſhed, but ſtill retained their <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being</hi> by vertue of that Law, and your ſelves hereditatory there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but not unto the Worke.</p>
               <p>Truly (Pious <hi>Brethren,)</hi> I commend your venerable Sanctities, that are ſo provident, both for your profit and eaſe, you are very wiſe in your Generation; indeed it is the profit that fills your ſpitts
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113342:11"/>
with Pigges, Capons, &amp;c. But <hi>(holy Brethren,)</hi> it is againſt all equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and juſtice, <hi>to require the wages of a Worke, and not to doe the Worke; If a man offer ſuch wages for ſuch a Worke, bee that will juſtly claime the one, muſt doe the other, for his</hi> equity <hi>to the</hi> Title <hi>of the one, is founded in the labour of the other, and not doe another kind of worke, the wages whereof he ſuppoſeth is not ſo profitable, and exact the wages of the former, which he conceiveth is more profitable,</hi> that is, <hi>Doe the Worke of the</hi> Goſpel <hi>for the wages of the</hi> Law; <hi>this will not ſerve, there is neither</hi> equity <hi>in the one, nor</hi> Conſcience <hi>in the other; If you will have</hi> Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wages, <hi>you muſt doe</hi> Law worke; <hi>If you will have</hi> Goſpel-worke, <hi>which you deem to be more eaſy, then you muſt be con ent with</hi> Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wages, <hi>though not ſo profitable, if therewith you will not be content, you muſt leave the Worke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having tryed your <hi>Moſaicall Title</hi> from the Levitticall Prieſthood for your <hi>Divine Right,</hi> to the <hi>Exaction of Tythes,</hi> and finding all your reaſonings from thence empty and ayerie deluſions, wherewith you have over ſhaddowed your Policy and Deceit from the Peoples diſcerning, bearing them in hand with their <hi>Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> but not telling them for what, and to whom they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained: now let us trace you a little further, and try your <hi>Coſpel Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> and ſee what divine Influence it doth communicate to your <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Title;</hi> it may be, you will be found as deluſive there, as you were under your Legall Pretences; which done, I ſhall adventure upon your laſt and mame Battery it ſelf, <hi>The Ordinance for Tythes:</hi> and if I diſmount you there, your beſt ſhift will be, <hi>The good will of the Vulgar,</hi> and glad you can have that at a pinch, to piece out your <hi>Jure Divine,</hi> and preſerve your SANCTITIES from <hi>Mechanick Druggery:</hi> I will not too much (if you will but pleaſe mine <hi>Holyneſs,</hi> and beare with the contrary-minded) make tryall of your Right unto that Title, for ſhould I, you might rue the day that ever MARTIN was borne; though I confeſſe, you have little cauſe to celebrate his Nativity with rejoycing; for it is to be feared, from what he hath already done, Sir JOHN will have much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe to get Poſſeſſion of his FATHERS <hi>Inheritance</hi> with Peace. But to omit trifling, and to returne to our intended purpoſe, and try what the <hi>Apoſtolicall Writings</hi> afford either, <hi>Pro</hi> or <hi>con.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sect">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113342:11"/>
               <head>SECTION II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Clergies EVANGELICALL TITLE of <hi>Jure Divino</hi> to their Exaction of TYTHES.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>Wee read, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 16. 20, 27, 28, 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT <hi>Paul</hi> having ſent to <hi>Epheſus</hi> for the Elders of the <hi>Church,</hi> told them, that he had <hi>kept nothing back that was profitable to them, teaching from houſe to houſe, and that he had not ſhunned, to declare unto them all the</hi> COUNCELL <hi>of</hi> GOD; and therefere bid them, <hi>Take heed, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him would come grievous Wolves among them, not ſparing the Flock:</hi> And to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> cap. 1. 8. hee faith, <hi>Though wee, or an Angel from heaven preach any other Goſpel unto you, then that which wee have preached unto you, let him be accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in all his Writings, and in the whole Book of the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wee doe not find any Declaration of his for ſupplying any neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Churches, whether of Elders, or any other Members, by the <hi>Exaction of Tythes,</hi> but his ORDER for ſuch <hi>ſupply</hi> is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for to the <hi>Corinthians, Epiſt. 1. cap. 16. 1, 2.</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>Now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Collection for the Saints, as I have given Order to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of</hi> Galatia, <hi>even ſo doe yee, upon the firſt day of the Week, let every one of you lay by him in ſtore, as God hath proſpered bin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and in the 2 <hi>Epiſt. cap. 9. 1. 5. 7) For as touching the Miniſtring the SAINTS, I thought it neceſſary to export the Brethren, that they would got before unto you, and make up before-hand your bounty, whereof wee had notice before, that the ſome might be ready, as a matter of hounty, not of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe: Every man according as hee parpoſeth in his heart ſo let him give, not grudgingly, or of neceſſity, for GOD loveth a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full giver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113342:12"/>
And this was Gods ORDINANCE, for the ſupply of the Saints, declared and delivered by <hi>Paul</hi> unto the <hi>Churches;</hi> therefore he that preacheth any other manner of <hi>ſupply,</hi> then what is <hi>voluntary,</hi> or <hi>matter of bounty,</hi> as of <hi>neceſſity,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Exaction of Tythes,</hi> or the like, is to be <hi>accurſed; If any man ſhall adde unto theſe things, God ſhall adde unto him the Plagnes that are written in this booke,</hi> Deur. 4. 2. Prov. 30. 6. Reu. 22. 18. So that the taking away this <hi>Ordinance of Voluntary contribution,</hi> and in the room thereof, violently intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>compulſive Exaction of Tythes,</hi> is guilty of this curſe <hi>Paul</hi> proncunceth, and of all the <hi>plagues that are written in the book of</hi> GOD: for no other <hi>Ordinance,</hi> then that of <hi>Voluntary contribution</hi> was <hi>committed</hi> by him for <hi>ſupply</hi> of any of the <hi>Saints</hi> unto the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> and he (as he told them) <hi>kept nothing back, but declared unto them the whole Councell of God,</hi> ſo that no place is left of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> for any other <hi>ſupply,</hi> then what hee hath already declared: Therefore what will become of our Clergy <hi>Tythe-mongers,</hi> that tell us, <hi>Tythes is an Ordinance of the Goſpel,</hi> and not <hi>Pauls</hi> Ordinance of <hi>Contribution,</hi> when God calls them to an account? I am afraid they will be found ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> foretold the <hi>Elders of Epheſus</hi> would come in amongſt them, even <hi>greedy Wolves, not ſparing the flock,</hi> ſuch as will not leave them to their bounty, to the purpoſe of their heart, but count that too beggarly and baſe for their <hi>Pontificall cloath,</hi> ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch a ſupply as contemptible and diſhonourable to their bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and Places, and therefore anſwerable to their ambitious <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity Spirits,</hi> muſt kick <hi>Pauls</hi> out of place, and countenanee, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce, and conſtitute a more ſtately, authorative, commanding Ordinance of their owne, exacting, and extorting their ſupply by compulſion, not ſparing <hi>the flock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (deer <hi>Brethren)</hi> take the wholſome and Pious advice of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>MARTIN;</hi> If you be Saints (as you pretend your ſelves to be) and as it is eſſentiall to a <hi>Presbyter or Elder</hi> of a <hi>Church)</hi> doe no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger adde or diminiſh from the pure <hi>unalterable Ordinances</hi> of God, and be content with what <hi>Paul</hi> ordained for the <hi>Saints,</hi> to <hi>ſupply the Saints Neceſſities;</hi> I deſire your <hi>Sanctities,</hi> as you tender the Piety of your cloth, the reverend eſtimate of your <hi>Name,</hi> and reputation of <hi>Saints,</hi> for I know you would be ſo entred into the <hi>Rubricks</hi> of our eſtimation, <hi>even Saints by calling,</hi> or Trade; approve your ſelves to be <hi>Saints</hi> indeed, and be content, as the <hi>Saints</hi> ever were and are, with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113342:12"/>
                  <hi>toe portion of the Saints, in all their neceſſities,</hi> which is evident, was and is unalterable to this day, <hi>the Voluntary contribution of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by Collection every firſt day of the Week,</hi> and to this, and to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of ſupply from the Churches, can the Saints lay any claim of <hi>Divine Right.</hi> Therefore if you will challenge any portion from them, <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> it muſt be no other, then the reſult of their <hi>bounties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Primative Inſtitution</hi> and Practice, <hi>of the Firſt Day Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection for the generall neceſſities of the Saints,</hi> was continued amongſt the <hi>Evangelicall Churches,</hi> till about 200 yeeres after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> about which time it degenerated from <hi>weekly</hi> to <hi>monthly,</hi> but not from the nature of the thing, as from <hi>free bounty,</hi> to <hi>coercive exaction;</hi> for <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> who lived about that time, <hi>Apalogetic. 39. &amp; 42.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam unuſquiſque ſtipem men ſtruadie, vel cum velit, &amp; ſi modo poſſit, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit: nam nemo compellisus, ſed ſponte confert, &amp;c.</hi> Every one <hi>monthly,</hi> or when he would, provided he were able, gave a <hi>competent portion;</hi> for no man was compelled to this or that <hi>quantity, but gave of his own accord;</hi> And ſuch their <hi>Contributions</hi> or <hi>Offerings</hi> were devoted <hi>to the Neceſſities of the Poore</hi> SAINTS <hi>in generall; For the goods and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the</hi> Church <hi>were antiently reputed and ſtiled,</hi> The Proviſion of the POORE, <hi>even till about 800. years after</hi> CHRIST; <hi>and till then, no payment of</hi> Tythes <hi>in the Chriſtian Churches can be proved, but indeed, about that time, Chriſtians degenerating from their Primitive Purity, growing more careleſſe, ignorant, and remiſſe, and their leaders, more covetous and ambitious, it intruded it ſelf through their Policy here and there amongſt ſome Societies, proſeſſing themſelves</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>but was not generall, but at length, through the bewitching ſubtillty of their Prieſts, the people were infattuated into ſuch a blinde zeal thereof, that it became in ſuch an high adoration, that men of great Poſſeſſions would give unto ſuch a Prieſt, ſuch an Abbot. &amp;c. the</hi> Tenthes <hi>of ſuch and ſuch a</hi> Poſſeſſion, <hi>for his ſoul, the ſoul of his Wife, the ſouls of his Children, or the ſouls of ſuch and ſuch freinds,</hi> and after this manner <hi>Tythes</hi> crept in, and overſpread moſt part of this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> having their riſe, ouſtome and practiſe firſt from poore depraved ſeduced ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <hi>Soules,</hi> through the ſorceries of their <hi>Pollitick Leaders,</hi> and by them were thus conferr'd upon the Churches by their voluntary <hi>Act:</hi> which <hi>Donations,</hi> at length were confirmed by the <hi>Common-Law,</hi> and a generall <hi>exaction thereof through the whole Kingdome, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113342:13"/>
upon the Clergy,</hi> to be theirs <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> whereby they no longer held, or claim'd them by vertue of Donation, but by <hi>Divine Right,</hi> and thus by degrees they patch'd up their Goddeſſe <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> unto their unjuſt Exaction of TYTHES, concerning which the Reader may receive further ſatisfaction in the peruſall of Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> Hiſtory of TYTHES.</p>
               <p>Whence by the way may be obſerved, what a ravening greedy ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration our Prieſts ever have been, and this preſent Generation is as like them, as <hi>if they were ſpit out of their mouthes,</hi> that wee have cauſe verily to beleeve, that at their Ordination, in ſtead of that ridiculous foppery, and mocking of Chriſt, in <hi>breathing on them the</hi> holy Spirit, they breath'd into them their own ſpirit of coverouſnes, which makes the children ſo like their fathers, ſo expert at this godly <hi>Legerdemaine,</hi> this Pious <hi>Theft,</hi> as ever their Predeceſſors were, and can as neatly challenge it of Divine Right, as ever either the Papall or Epiſcopall <hi>Vermine</hi> before them could; indeed, it is eſſentiall to their colour, they'l never leave their ſpirituall thievery, as long as their coats are <hi>black,</hi> or their girdles be worne about their midles, a cubite below their deſerts; for why ſhould not <hi>black Thieves,</hi> as well as other coloured Thieves, have the recompence of their reward?</p>
               <p>But that we might the more admire their greedineſſe, let us look back, and recall to our memories the <hi>Primative time,</hi> where (as wee have given a touch,) we ſhall ſee, that all the goods of the Church were devoted to the uſe and ſupply of the poore, and generall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of the Church, and were ſo improved, which if we paralell with our times, we ſhall finde a direct Antipathy, a vaſt diſparity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, as betwixt light and darkneſſe: We ſhall finde amongſt us greater Eccleſiaſticall Donations, larger revenues, and wealth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed (though out of an ignorant blinde zeal for ſiniſter ends) upon Churches (whoſe proper end being voluntary <hi>Contribution,</hi> is of Primative Inſtitution unto ſuch pious ends, as the relief of the poor, and the like,) and amongſt us an abundance of Poore, Fatherleſſe, Widdowes, &amp;c. in every Parochiall Church, even ready to periſh for want of <hi>ſupply,</hi> and yet through the mercileſſe covetouſneſſe of the Prieſts, notwithſtanding ſuch large proviſion for them, they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver once taſte the ſweetneſſe of ſuch charitable Church-Donations, wherein they have aproper Intereſt of lively hood being members of ſuch Churches, for ſuch is the avarice and greedineſſe of the Prieſts,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113342:13"/>
that they are become ſole Treaſurers thereof, and cram all into the waſt ſtore-houſe of their ungodly dirty Panches, and devoure up the <hi>Right</hi> of the POORE, the Fatherleſſe, Widdows, Strangers, &amp;c. on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſometimes at their venerable Doores, forſooth, ſanctify their Pitchers with a Reverend Meſſe of Pottage, to evidence their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allity, how they are given to Hoſpitallity, and ſend not the hungry and needy empty away: my bleſſing and benediction be upon you all, my dear Birds all, but I hope I ſhall never trouble your doores.</p>
               <p>Further, they are not herewith content, thus to rob the Poore of their Right, but from thoſe their miſerable poor members, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort even the Tenth of their penurious increaſe: Here for inſtance, I could fix a ſecond Century of Cormorant Prieſts in this kind, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of the heard of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> ſince the <hi>edition</hi> of the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for</hi> TYTHES; A poor man cannot have 2. or 3. hens and a <hi>cock,</hi> but they will have the tenth <hi>tread,</hi> to be <hi>jure divino,</hi> at leaſt they will have 2. egges for a hen, 3. for a cock, 2. for a duck, 3. for a drake, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But to omit this, let us a little further examine the Evangelicall Authority and Injunctions concerning the maintenance of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Miniſtery: and for this, let us returne unto the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> comparing <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. with <hi>verſ.</hi> 33, 34, 35. Which declareth, that <hi>Paul</hi> having ſent for the <hi>Elders</hi> of the Church of <hi>Epheſits,</hi> hee told them ſaying, I have coveted no mans ſilver or gold, or apparrell, yea your ſelves know, that theſe hands have miniſtred unto my neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to them that were with me, I have ſhewed you all things, how that ſo labouring (to wit, with your hands) yea, (namely the <hi>Elders,)</hi> ought to ſupport the weak, and to remember the words of our Lord Jeſus, how he ſaid, It is more bleſſed to give, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: and to this adde, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 9. Ye remember our labouring night and day, becauſe we would not be chargeable, &amp;c. and 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 8, 10. We did not eat any mans bread for nought, but wrought with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and travell night and day, that we might not be chargeable to any of you; for even when we were with you, this wee commanded you, that if any would not work, he ſhould not eat. From whence is evident, that he laid a neceſſity of working upon them, for declaring to the <hi>Elders</hi> of Epheſus, how he ſupplyed the neceſſities of them that were with him, by the labour of his hands, ſets himſelf forth as a Patterne to the very <hi>Elders</hi> themſelves therein, and thereupon puts them in minde of his former Precepts in that kind, ſaying,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113342:14"/>
                  <hi>I have ſhewed you all things, how that ſo labouring, yee might to ſupport the weak; and the</hi> equity <hi>of this</hi> Ordinance <hi>unto them, hee groundeth upon the ſaying of CHRIST;</hi> It is more bleſſed to give, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: <hi>from whence is undenyable, that the</hi> Elders <hi>or</hi> Presbyters <hi>were bound to take him for a Patterne in that practice, and that from him they had received Order for it, as their duties, becauſe it was a more bleſſed thing to give then to receive, and this was given to the</hi> Presbyters <hi>of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, <hi>that they ſhould endeavour after the more</hi> bleſſed thing, <hi>that their hands, as</hi> Paul <hi>did, ſhould</hi> adminiſter to their neceſſities, and to them that were with them; <hi>and this was an Ordinance grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the</hi> equity <hi>of</hi> CHRIST'S <hi>ſaying, not to be repealed, altered, added or deminiſhed under the penalty of all the</hi> Plagues that are written in the Book of GOD: <hi>for as he had received from the Lord, ſo declared he unto them, and kept nothing back from them, that was profitable, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to them the whole</hi> Councell of God: <hi>Therefore, whatſoever hee delivered unto them, was the</hi> Councell of God, <hi>and he delivered this ORDER to the</hi> Elders <hi>for the miniſtration</hi> to their neceſſities, <hi>it muſt needs be from the</hi> Councell of God: <hi>ſo that this muſt either be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be</hi> Gods Ordinance, <hi>or elſe</hi> Paul <hi>did not declare the</hi> Will of God, <hi>at leaſt, not the whole Councell</hi> of God: <hi>But if</hi> Tythes <hi>were ordained by God for them, then he kept back ſomewhat of the</hi> Councell of God <hi>from them; for neither to them, nor to any other of the Churches did he declare any</hi> Ordinance for the true payment of TYTHES, <hi>like that of the</hi> LORDS <hi>and</hi> COMMONS <hi>Aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore, this Ordinance of working with their hands, is in force to</hi> Elders, <hi>or</hi> Presbyters of Churches. <hi>But indeed, I cannot much blame our</hi> Presbyters, <hi>conſidering their breeding, that they ſo much abominate this primative</hi> Ordinance, <hi>is too inferiour, mechanick and diſhonourable to their Calling; for we muſt conſider our</hi> Presbyters <hi>are</hi> Univerſity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>not like the mechanick Primative</hi> Presbyters, <hi>like</hi> Fiſhermen, Tent-makers, <hi>ſuch inferiour fellowes as</hi> Paul, <hi>the</hi> ſcumme or off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuring of the World; <hi>ours are of a more venerable honourable</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>and therefore it highly concernes them in inſenſe their hearers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all mechanick Preachers, as</hi> Coblers, Tinkers, Chimney-ſwoep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Bellows-menders, <hi>and the like, for ſhould ſuch Preachers, (as after</hi> Pauls <hi>example, works for their livings, with their own hands) come into credit and reputation, and game acceptance amongſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113342:14"/>
our lazie Preachers, that live upon the ſwear of other mens browes, notwithſtanding God hath enabled them to worke with their own hands, muſt conclude to give place unto ſuch; for if the people did not ſo much dote upon their Spiritualities as if the Word of God came only to them, and onely from them, and were not as wel communicative to Tradeſmen, but ſhould in differently entertain the Communications of God in any ſort of People, though <hi>Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Tent-makers, Coblers, Weavers</hi> or the like, then the adoration of their Order and Cloth, would grow out of date, their Rever end eſteem among the People vaniſh <hi>like a miſt before the riſing Sunne</hi> for truly a leathern Jacket, a blue Apron, or ſuch other Enſigne of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, would better become a Pulpit, then a black Caſlock, a payre of Lilly-white Hands, or ſuch like badges of Idleneſſe, for that would import the Preaching of the Goſpel <hi>freely,</hi> without charge unto any, meerly out of Conſcience, and not for <hi>filthy lucre,</hi> where as this can evidence nothing but the direct contrary; for who can judge that ſuch a one workes with his owne-hands that he might be chargeable to none? And thus much by the way, onely to let the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their drift in railing againſt Tradeſ men that communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate (like good diſpoſers <hi>of the manifold graces of Gods)</hi> of the ability that God hath given them, to others.</p>
               <p>But leaſt I ſhould appeare in this Injunction of <hi>working,</hi> to wreſt <hi>Pauls</hi> intent beyond its proper extent, I alſo aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that like hath not ſo given it in charge, and impos'd it ſo upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on <hi>Fres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> of Churches, as in no caſe to admit of a mitigation thereof, as if there were no right of ſupply upon any occaſion or condition, but what they acquired by their owne hands, at all unto them; but he enjoyneth this Ordinance of <hi>working</hi> upon them, but in caſe of poſſibility thereof, not in caſe of defection of nature, lameneſſe, ſickneſſe, impriſonment, or the like, even as hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dameth for the reſt of the poore; for all are commanded to <hi>worke,</hi> none exempted, and for ſuch cauſes of imbicility and miſery, or for want of <hi>worke,</hi> and the like, the contribution of the Churches was ordained; and one as well as another; Elders as well as People, all are to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that they may not be chargeable, for it is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bleſſed <hi>thing to give then to receive,</hi> and this they are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at with <hi>Paul,</hi> though it be with trayell and labour; night and day; no labour or paines, early or lace, is to be ſhunned, that this may be attained; and none
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113342:15"/>
are to receive the <hi>ſupply</hi> of <hi>Bounty,</hi> neither in equity is it due unto any, but in caſe of <hi>neceſsity,</hi> it was never ordained for redundancy and ſuperfluity, and to make one ſort more Wealthy, Lordly, and better arraied and fed then the reſt, but to <hi>ſupply</hi> the extremities of miſeries or that there might be a moderate competency of ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance amongſt the meaneſt, that none might want that which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for their naturall ſubſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> giveth this <hi>Ordinance of working,</hi> and propoſeth himſelf as an example therein unto the <hi>Elders,</hi> for their imitation, as the more excellent way, by how much the more better it is to give then to receive; for to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> in the like caſe he ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neither did wee eat any mans bread for naught, but wrought with labour and travell night and day, that we might not be chargeable unto any of you, not becauſe we have not Power, but to make our ſelves an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample unto you to follow us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence it is evident, That though they had a POWER, yet this was the moſt excellent patterne for them to follow, and they were to make him their enſample, which hee propoſed to them as a <hi>precept</hi> for their imitation: Now what this <hi>Power</hi> was, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth upon inquiry, and that it could extend it ſelf no further then is diſcovered in the <hi>Word,</hi> is undenyable, and for any other <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> extant in the Writings of the Apoſtles, then to <hi>receive ſupply as poore Saints,</hi> we doe not read of; therefore it could be no other <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> he meant of; and the poor <hi>Saints</hi> have no other power, or can lay claime of <hi>Divine Right</hi> unto any ſuch <hi>ſupply,</hi> but in <hi>caſes of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> walking was anſwer able hereto; for he never received any thing of them, but in ſuch caſes, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 16, 17. <hi>For even in</hi> Theſſalonica <hi>ye ſent once and againe unto my neceſsities, not becauſe I deſire a gift, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 9. <hi>For that which was lacking to me, the Brethren which came from</hi> Macedonia <hi>ſupplyed:</hi> which compared with other places, declaring <hi>his working night and day with his own hands,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2. 9. 1. Cor. 11, 12. is very evident, that his <hi>power of receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other ſupply</hi> then ſuch as was by his own hands, was in caſes of ſuch <hi>neceſsities</hi> as he could not ſupply himſelf, and that was not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113342:15"/>
                  <hi>the ſupply of Exaction or force,</hi> like this of <hi>Tythes,</hi> but of <hi>Free-gift,</hi> Phil. 4. 15, 16, 17. <hi>No Church communicated with me, as concerning gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and receiving, but ye only, &amp;c.</hi> and he endeavoured to the <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his power, not to be burthenſome.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>and</hi> cap. 12, 13, 14, 16, 17, 18. 1 Theſſ. 2. 9. <hi>and</hi> cap. 3. 8, 10. From all which places it is undenyable, that his utmoſt endeavour was, not to be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome; for he ſaith, <hi>it were better for him to die, then that any man ſhould make his glorying therein voide, that where hee preach'd the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, there he might make the Goſpel of Chriſt without charge,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 15.</p>
               <p>All which conſidered together, it plainly appeareth; that his <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> was but in <hi>caſes of neceſsity,</hi> when he could not helpe it; for <hi>woe</hi> was unto him, <hi>if he did not make the Goſpel free, if poſsibly he could, though with his own hands he wrought night and day,</hi> verſ. 18. hee ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is my reward then? Verily, that when I preach the Goſpel, I may make the Goſpel of Chriſt without charge, that I abuſe not my power in the Goſpel;</hi> whence obſerve, <hi>That if hee ſhould not have endeavoured to have made the Goſpel free, he ſhould have abuſed his</hi> power; <hi>ſo that his power could onely lie in</hi> caſes of neceſſity; for otherwiſe he ſhould not have endeavoured to <hi>make it free,</hi> and ſo ſhould have abuſed his <hi>power,</hi> that is, <hi>ſtretch'd it beyond its bounds.</hi> For if this <hi>power</hi> were wholly to rely upon them for maintenance, like this <hi>power</hi> that our <hi>Presbyters</hi> enforce upon us, then if he ſhould in all places where he preached the Goſpel, have relyed wholly upon them for his <hi>ſupply,</hi> and not at all endeavoured with the labour of his owne hands to have made it without <hi>charge,</hi> when hee could for preaching tended thereon, he had not in ſo doing abuſed his <hi>power;</hi> but kept himſelf within the warrant, authority &amp; property thereof; for that which is done by the proper Right and Authority of a Power, cannot be an Abuſe of the <hi>power,</hi> but an abſolute execution and fulfilling there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to an abuſe of a Power, muſt either be a Tranſgreſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it, that is, doing more then it authorizes, or elſe a neglect, or comming ſhort of it; and one of theſe two muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be, or elſe the POWER cannot poſſibly be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113342:16"/>
Now the abuſe of a <hi>Power,</hi> (Whether in either of the extreames;) in not the <hi>Power</hi> it ſelf, but the <hi>power</hi> is preciſely confined to its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or warrant, for the authority gives beeing to the <hi>power,</hi> and the <hi>power,</hi> as it cannot come ſhort, neither can it goe beyond its <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> for ſo ſhould it miſſe of its Beeing; for in the <hi>authority</hi> or <hi>command,</hi> the <hi>power</hi> liveth, moveth, and hath it beeing: Therefore as <hi>Paul</hi> was not to come ſhort, ſo was he not to goe beyond his <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,</hi> for in ſo doing, he ſhould have abuſed it, ſo that his <hi>power</hi> could only be in caſes of neceſſity; if he had refuſed ſupply in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, or taken it when by his induſtry he could have prevented it without dammage to his Preaching, hee had abuſed his <hi>power,</hi> therefore his <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> of living on the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> was but when otherwiſe he could not acquire it with prejudice to his preaching: He was to have his <hi>ſupport</hi> and <hi>livelyhead</hi> by it, when as without it, he could not procure it: So that the Patrimony of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is onely of <hi>Divine Right</hi> due unto neceſſity, and therein onely have the Miniſters thereof <hi>power</hi> to live on it, like as the reſt of the <hi>Saints</hi> had; and thought they were better abilify'd with Spirituall gifts from God; they were not therefore to be paid for them, to live lazily and idlely, but as they had <hi>freely received from the Lord,</hi> ſo were they <hi>freely to Admineller thereof in to the People,</hi> for <hi>God loveth a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full giver,</hi> let it be in what kind of duty ſoever; they were not to make <hi>a gaine of the Goſpel,</hi> to make a Trade of it, like as our <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> doe, and ſelf it out by Penny-worths, or enter into the Office thereof, for their own advantage, or lively hood-ſake, but to Preach it <hi>fecely</hi> out of Conſcience, with ſinceer hearts, <hi>not looking upon the to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, bid of gaining fonts into God,</hi> not abuſing of their <hi>power.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> further confirmeth this ſaying, <hi>and this I doe, for the Goſpels ſake, that I might be parlker thereof with you;</hi> which plainly imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, That if he had not endeavoured to make the <hi>Goſpel free,</hi> but abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his <hi>power,</hi> in relying wholy upon it, that then he ſhould not have been partaker of the Goſpel with them, but ſhould have loſt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Goſpel, and himſelf <hi>become a caſt-away,</hi> therefore woe was unto him, it he did not ſo endeavour to make it without <hi>charge:</hi> Now two things are to be conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That his <hi>power</hi> would not extend to his woe and condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but for him not to endeavour to make the Goſpel without <hi>charge,</hi> was woe, was condemnation to him; Therefore his <hi>Power</hi> could
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113342:16"/>
not extend thereto, that is, <hi>To live wholly upon the charge of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> not (when it lay in his <hi>power,</hi> without prejudice to his preaching) endeavouring the contrary, under penalty of his Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That our <hi>Fresbyters</hi> now have not a greater <hi>power,</hi> or <hi>Divine Right</hi> unto ſupply, then <hi>Paul</hi> had: But wee ſee his <hi>power</hi> extended no further then in <hi>caſes of neceſſity,</hi> for then only he could claime it out of a good Conſcience, and of <hi>Divine Right:</hi> Therefore our <hi>Preshyters</hi> can claime no other to themſelves <hi>Jure Divine</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Premiſed, it followeth then, that the <hi>ſupply</hi> whereto the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> had <hi>power,</hi> was not as they were <hi>Elders</hi> or <hi>Presbyters,</hi> but as they were <hi>poore Saints;</hi> my Reaſons are.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is no other <hi>ſupply</hi> extant in the Scriptures, then ſuch as is in common to the <hi>poore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There was never any <hi>portion</hi> ſet out for them, as thus, and thus much ſhall be for the <hi>Elders,</hi> in ſuch and ſuch a condition, ſo that one as an <hi>Elder</hi> might have challenged the <hi>portion of an Elder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They had no right to <hi>ſupply,</hi> but in <hi>caſe of neceſſity,</hi> which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implyes, That it was onely as they were <hi>poore men,</hi> not as they were <hi>Elders,</hi> for ſo their right thereto had been at all times, in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as well as in want, when they could work, as well as when they could not; for they are <hi>Elders</hi> in one condition, as well as in the other, <hi>plenty</hi> no more then <hi>want</hi> could alter their <hi>Elderſhip;</hi> and what is due unto <hi>Elderſhip,</hi> is due at one time as well as another, by vertus thereof at all times having a power thereto.</p>
               <p>Put wee ſee, they never had <hi>power</hi> in this kinde, but in <hi>caſes of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity:</hi> Therefore not as <hi>Elders,</hi> but as <hi>poore Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. A neceſſity was laid upon them <hi>to Preach the Goſpel, under the penalty of a</hi> Woe <hi>and a</hi> Curſe, <hi>whether they were paid or no:</hi> therefore the payment was not eſſentiall <hi>to the Office, for the Office</hi> was to be executed without it. Further, if it were eſſentially the wager of the Worke, the Worke could not be required under ſuch a penalty, and of neceſſity of the wages thereof, for in <hi>equity</hi> there is as much neceſſity of the wages of a Worke, as of the Worke; But wages, or not Wages, there: was a neceſſity of the Worke: As they were <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> there was a neceſſity of Preaching, but not as <hi>Elders of exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a maintenance;</hi> Therefore this <hi>Power</hi> was not as they were <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or Preachers,</hi> but as they were <hi>poore Elders or Preachers:</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113342:17"/>
their <hi>Church Portion</hi> lay in the Poor-mans Boxe, having no <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> thereto, but as <hi>Poore-men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. That though this <hi>proviſion</hi> be for the <hi>poore Saints,</hi> yet all the <hi>Saints,</hi> Elders as well as others, are commanded to worke, and <hi>Elders in ſpeciall;</hi> for, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the ELDERS, <hi>I have ſhewed you all things, how that ſo labouring,</hi> (to wit, after his example,) <hi>yet ought to ſupport the weake:</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, Even <hi>ye,</hi> that are <hi>Elders,</hi> as well as <hi>wee</hi> that are <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or as any others: And to <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Brethren</hi> of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> none exempted, he ſaith; <hi>This we comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you, That if any man would not worke, neither ſhould he eat,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 10. But were a <hi>full Supply</hi> due unto <hi>Elders,</hi> as they were <hi>Elders;</hi> then, there were no need of laying upon them the <hi>duty of working</hi> with their hands, after <hi>Pauls</hi> example; for, to provide all things to their hands, for their full Supply, and yet command them to worke with their hands for it, were a ſlat contradiction.</p>
               <p n="6">6. As well might the <hi>Saints</hi> lay claim to it, <hi>as they are Saints,</hi> as thoſe to lay claim to it, <hi>as they are Elders,</hi> to wit, barely becauſe they are <hi>Elders,</hi> that therefore they muſt have it; yea, better might the <hi>Saints</hi> claim it as <hi>Saints;</hi> for it was never termed, the <hi>portion for El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> but <hi>Collection for the Saints,</hi> or the like: but, it is neither due to the <hi>one,</hi> nor to the <hi>other</hi> in <hi>that kinde,</hi> but to <hi>both,</hi> (Elders and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,) as they are <hi>poore Saints</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas <hi>poore-men,</hi> this is a pittifull caſe for our <hi>Presbyters;</hi> I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, they will rather all <hi>un-Saint</hi> themſelves, then ſuffer ſuch a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable beggarly diſaſter: But we muſt conſider, it was not <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-time</hi> in Pauls dayes, when the <hi>Saints portion</hi> was ſet out; but it is otherwiſe now; <hi>Ergo,</hi> of neceſſity now an Ordinance for <hi>Tythes</hi> muſt be theirs <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If therefore their <hi>Title</hi> be but as <hi>poor Saint-Elders, poor Saint-Presbyters,</hi> or the like, then <hi>Presbyters</hi> muſt be content to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as indeed they be) the <hi>Almeſ-people</hi> of the Church, and for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration to their neſſeſſities, no other then the <hi>Armes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> is the <hi>patrimony,</hi> that they can claime right of inheritance unto; they may not in the leaſt extort from, or exact upon their <hi>Almis-Maſters,</hi> more then ſhall ſeem good unto their charitable diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; they muſt not goe to <hi>Law</hi> with them, ſend Officers to <hi>plunder their Goods,</hi> riſie their houſes, impriſon their Perſons or the like, in caſe they cannot have their deſires fulfill'd: for my part, I ſhall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113342:17"/>
count ſuch an <hi>Almes-man,</hi> let it be <hi>Almes-Presbyter,</hi> or what he will, no better then a <hi>Thiefe by the High-way-ſide,</hi> and that in equity hee hath more Title to the Galldwes, then to the <hi>Almes</hi> of the People, or one penny out of the <hi>Poore-mans-box.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="objection">
                  <head>Objection.</head>
                  <p>1 Cor. 9. 46, 7, 9, 14. <hi>Have wee not power to eat and to drinke? or I only, and</hi> Barnabas, <hi>have not we power to forbear working? who feedeth a fock, and eateth not of the milke of the flock? for it is written in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the Corne:</hi> Doth God take care for Oxen? <hi>even ſo the Lord hath ordained, That they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live on the Goſpel.</hi> From hence the Clergy juſtify the whiteneſſe and ſoftneſſe of their hands, as if from thence they had an utter diſpenſation from work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and an abſolute <hi>divine Title</hi> to a redundancy of Proviſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Though he ſaith, <hi>have not we power to forbear working?</hi> we muſt not think that it was an exorbitant unlimitted power, extending to the tranſgreſſion of <hi>the rule</hi> of <hi>equity,</hi> for ſo it ſhould have been a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>power;</hi> and to have ſuch an opinion of any power that is from God, ſuch as this was, is no leſſe then <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> for as he is a God of equity and juſtice, ſo are allhis wayes <hi>equall and juſt;</hi> and that onely ſinfull which is not bounded within the compaſſe of equity, which is not any wayes computable with him or his <hi>wayes:</hi> therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reaſonably be imagined, that his power of <hi>forbearance of worke</hi> could be an <hi>unlimmited power,</hi> tranſgreſſing the <hi>bounds of equity:</hi> and the <hi>Bule of equity</hi> concerning <hi>working,</hi> is, <hi>If any man will not worke, neither ſhould be eat,</hi> the equity of which <hi>rule</hi> is, That none ſhould be idle and lazie, and eat the <hi>bread of idleneſſe,</hi> and to ſuch a <hi>forbearance</hi> as this, like that of our belly-god Lordain Prieſts, wee cannot in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon conceive their <hi>power extended,</hi> for ſo it ſhould have tranſgreſſed the <hi>Rule of Equity,</hi> and had been an <hi>unjuſt power:</hi> but they muſt be laborious in their kind, for <hi>the duty of working</hi> gives title in <hi>equity</hi> to eating: it doth not in the leaſt give them a diſpenſation to idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; as, becauſe they were Miniſters of the Word, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were utterly exempted from Working, and might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>eat the bread of idleneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113342:18"/>
No, <hi>Dear Brethren:</hi> In <hi>equity</hi> and <hi>duty,</hi> all are, and ever were bound <hi>to get their bread by induſtry, the Apoſtles as well or others, elſe they had no</hi> divine Right <hi>to eat, ſo that no main that will eat, can fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be excuſed from the duty of</hi> working, <hi>then neceſſity enforces; and ever neceſſities God is compaſſionate, not requiring impoſſibilities, but in ſuch caſes hath provided a mittigation, according to mercy and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For</hi> neceſſity <hi>only can excuſe, and Further then neceſſity the excuſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not extend. Therefore they could no further be excuſed from working,</hi> that is, <hi>have further Power to forbear working with their hands, which was a duty, then by their Preaching they were hindred thereof; and ſo they were onely ſubject to neceſſity, not avoiding ſuch working, but when they were there to neceſsitated through Preaching the Goſpel, and ſo were in</hi> equity <hi>excuſeable, and bad a lawfull</hi> Power <hi>to forbeare for the Goſpel ſakes, for the more noble muſt take place of the leſſe, as of two</hi> evills, the leſſe is to be choſen, <hi>but both to be avoided if poſſible; ſo of two goods, the beſt is to be preferr'd, but both to be choſen, if poſſible; and where both cannot be, the greater in</hi> equity <hi>doth excuſe the leſſe: and ſo they bad a juſt power to forbeare; look how much in the diſcharge of the greater du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they were deprived of executing the leſſe, even ſo much were they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſable, and free; for the</hi> equity <hi>of their forbearing hand-labour, had its beeing from their Preaching: their Preaching being in it ſelf more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, made ſuch their forbeare once</hi> equall, <hi>by reaſmidi was a binderance therof, ſo that the</hi> equity <hi>of</hi> forbearance <hi>lay in the neceſsity of</hi> hindranee, <hi>and therein was bounded &amp; confined preciſely; for their forbearance of the one could not juſtly extend further then the binder once by the other; for where there is an impediment of working, there can be no excuſe of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for</hi> miniſhation <hi>to</hi> neceſſities; <hi>has ſo farre, as a man is free from impediment, ſo farre he is bound in duty of working, to ſupply his neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: So that though</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barhabas <hi>bad</hi> power <hi>to forbeare work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they might Freash the Goſpel,</hi> that is, <hi>improve time in Preaching which otherwiſe, (or in ſuch eminens neceſsity) they were bound to work in with their hands, to ſupply their neceſsities; yet for all this, they were bound to work, even with their bands, when poſſibly they could for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they might make the Goſpel without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> can an utter for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, or totall diſpenſotion from working was, not in, their power without limitation though to Preach they might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> are, yet when for Preaching, they could worke, they might not forbeare, i and when their preaching occaſioned their forbearance, then they were to live on the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113342:18"/>
then were not <hi>their murther to be minuted,</hi> then were they to beed, on <hi>the milke of the ſtick;</hi> for <hi>living on the Goſpel</hi> is entayl'd on <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel;</hi> the <hi>living</hi> extends to further then <hi>pretebing;</hi> for Preaching gives <hi>power</hi> and Title thereto; its <hi>eſſence</hi> and <hi>being</hi> is in Preathing; ſo that it cannot extend beyond that by which it hath its <hi>power</hi> and <hi>beeing,</hi> for ſhould it, it ſhould give beyond its <hi>power</hi> and <hi>beeing,</hi> and beyond is <hi>beeing,</hi> it can have no Title, or be longer eſteemed that <hi>power:</hi> ſo that look how farre they were deprived of Miniſtring to their neceſſities through Preaching, even ſo farre they had a right to the Peoples Adminiſtration, ſo farre they liad <hi>power</hi> to eate and to drinke, and no further; they were not to be Idle ſix dayes, and Preach on the ſeventh, and rely wholly upon the People, that was not in their <hi>power,</hi> nor yet in their practiſe; but when they had ſpare time from Preaching, they improv'd it in labouring for their <hi>bread,</hi> and at other times, when they were buſied in Preaching, were content with what was given them, receiving no more, but for their preſent neceſſities; they never had, or were to have any more then abare livelyhood; It is enough that the Diſciple be as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>and the ſervant as his Lord,</hi> Math. 10. 25. Now their Maſter li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in great humility, hee had never a Living of 4. or 5. hundred a yeere; never had a Houſe (like the Dean of <hi>Pauls)</hi> confirmed upon him by an Ordinance of PARL. <hi>The Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the Aire have neſts, but the Sonne of Man bad not whereon to lay his head,</hi> he lived in mean condition, was lowly and meek, hee never was trundled up and down <hi>(Presbyter-like)</hi> in a Coach, he ſate meekly <hi>upon an Aſſe, and a colt the foale of an Aſſe,</hi> Matth. 21. 5. and his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples lived the like life of humility; they made no further uſe of the World, then for their neceſſities, giving up themſelves wholly to the Goſpel, and were onely ſervants unto JESUS CHRIST, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their duties; <hi>for no man can ſerve two Maſters; for either hoe muſt hate the one, or love the other; or elſe, he will hold to the one, and deſpiſe the other: yee cannot ſerve God and Mammon,</hi> Mat. 6. 24. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Preachers muſt not be addicted to the world; be ſuch as plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mens goods, and rifle their houſes to ſpend upon their luſts and pleaſurs, or to be ſuch lazie idle Drones <hi>(like our Prieſts,)</hi> who take their pleaſure and eaſe all the week, onely give us an house, or two of <hi>Hodg-podge deluſion</hi> the Firſt Day; No, ſuch come not within the vaile of his acceptance, but ſuch rather that will both Preach and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113342:19"/>
work, that after their Preaching, will fall to mending old Bellowes, ſweeping of Chimneys, crying of Brooms, or Small-coale, or taking any ſuch-like honeſt courſe of livelyhood; ſuch are moſt fit to be the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt; yea, indeed it is from ſuch that wee receive the greateſt information in the myſteries of Jeſus Chriſt, in theſe dayes; for indeed, they are in his Ordinance, follow his Patterne and example of his Apoſtles; Not Preaching <hi>for filthy lucre,</hi> but out of Conſcience.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I deſire may be obſerved, That whereas he ſaith, <hi>Even ſo the Lord hath ordained, that they which Preach the Goſpel, ſhould live on the Goſpel;</hi> that from thence no other livelyhood may be concluded, then ſuch as the Lord himſelf had ordained for his Preachers, or that <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, that had as great a <hi>power</hi> as ever any of them had, did in them words, intend a <hi>power</hi> further then the Lords own Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now the Lords Ordination concerning thoſe that hee ſent forth into the world to Preach the Goſpel, both to the Twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and after them the 70. Diſciples, was, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 7, 8. to eate and to drinke ſuch things as were given, <hi>for the labourer is worthy of his hire,</hi> and <hi>into what City ſoever they entred, to eat ſuch things as were ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them by thoſe that did receive them,</hi> and <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 10, 11. they have the ſame Injunction, <hi>That in the City or houſe that was worthy, there they were to abide till they went thence, for the labourer is worthy of his meat:</hi> And this was all that ever the Lords Ordination pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for their <hi>living on the Goſpel,</hi> a power barely for their Victualls, or preſent neceſſities; even ſuch as was given them, was their hire, and no more, they had <hi>power</hi> given them <hi>to eate of their meat, for the Labourer was worthy of his meat;</hi> that was all that the Lords Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were to require for their hire, or to account themſelves worthy of: and thoſe that would not give this, they were but <hi>to ſhake off the duſt from their feet in teſtimony againſt them;</hi> farre different from the <hi>Plundering Ordinance for Tythes.</hi> And no other <hi>power</hi> then this <hi>Paul</hi> pleadeth for to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> for whereas he ſaith, <hi>Have wee not power to eate and to drinke?</hi> hee pleadeth it as one ſent from the Lord, <hi>to Preach unto the world,</hi> as verſ. 1. and 10. declareth; Now it is evident what <hi>power</hi> ſuch had to <hi>eating,</hi> and <hi>drinking;</hi> that is, of ſuch as was given them, of ſuch as was ſet before them; therefore no other can be concluded of <hi>Paul,</hi> but even as the Lord had ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and ſo, and no otherwiſe they that <hi>Preached the Goſpel, were to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113342:19"/>
live on the Goſpel:</hi> their neceſſities were to be looked upon, and for neceſſity ſake, they were meerly to be relieved; for the <hi>Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſun</hi> was for no more, and therewith his <hi>Servants</hi> were to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Therefore, their <hi>Title to it,</hi> was not ſimply as they were A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles or Preachers, but as Apoſtles and Preachers <hi>in neceſſity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus it is cleer, that all the <hi>Divine Right</hi> they had to other <hi>ſupply,</hi> then what they acquired by their hands, was but in <hi>caſes of neceſſity;</hi> and that was but to matters of <hi>bounty:</hi> So that it is moſt certaine, That the Preachers of our Lord, in their <hi>ſupply,</hi> are but as <hi>Almes-men,</hi> and ſo they are to live, and to be eſteemed, and eſteem themſelves to be no other, then the Almes-men of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="objection">
                  <head>Objection.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tythes were paid unto</hi> Melcheſedec, <hi>after whoſe Order was Chriſt our High-Prieſt for ever. Therefore, due unto the</hi> Evangelicall Order, as <hi>well as to the</hi> Levitticall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="solution">
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <p>If Tythes, which <hi>Abraham</hi> paid unto Melchezedea, were paid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as he was of that <hi>Everlaſting Order;</hi> it could be at the moſt but as he was Typically thereof; for he was no more then Typicall himſelf, ſhadowing out the Eternall High-Prieſt, CHRIST JESUS, for Chriſt was not that <hi>Melchezedec,</hi> but after the ſimilitude of that <hi>Melcheſedec,</hi> therefore, if after that ſimilitude, that is, after that <hi>ſhaddow</hi> or <hi>Type;</hi> then <hi>Melcheſedec's</hi> could not be the ſubſtance; for the thing ſimulating, cannot poſſibly be the thing ſimulated; ſo that the Prieſthood of CHRIST muſt needs be the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of that <hi>ſhadow,</hi> which <hi>Subſtance</hi> being come, the <hi>ſhaddow,</hi> with all its Appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, muſt vaniſh and be of no longer force, So that whereas it is ſaid, <hi>Abraham paid Tythes unto</hi> Melchezedec, it could be at moſt, but unto a <hi>Typicall Prieſthood,</hi> unto a Prieſt-hood <hi>which was but the ſhaddow of good things to come;</hi> and ſo, and no otherwiſe was it due unto the <hi>Levitticall Prieſthood,</hi> all whoſe ſervices were but <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>ſhaddows,</hi> ſerving unto the example and ſhaddow of heavenly things; and to ſuch Miniſters, for ſuch <hi>ſervices,</hi> was a commandement to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive TYTHES according to the Law:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113342:20"/>
Whereto Tythes were due, and which had a Commandement to receive them; therefore there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law, and mutter diſannulling of the Commandemour going before; which Commandement brought within its authority, the impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of TYTHES upon the People, for the Text ſaith, <hi>the ſonnes of</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi, <hi>who received the Prieſthood, had a Commandemens to take Tythes;</hi> now the Commandement ceaſing, the equity of their Exaction muſt needs ceaſe; ſo that now they cannot by <hi>Levite</hi> or any other, be chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged of <hi>Divine Right;</hi> for the challenging them now by <hi>Divine Right,</hi> is not onely a reduction to the Levitticall Prieſthood, but a denyall of this Jeſus to be an High-Prieſt <hi>for ever after the Order of</hi> Melcheſedec; implying, that the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of that <hi>ſhaddow</hi> is not come; for the paying of that which was proper to the ſimilitude or Type, ſheweth that the <hi>ſimilitude</hi> or <hi>Type</hi> is ſtill in force, and ſo the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance not come; for while the <hi>ſhaddow</hi> is in force, there is no place for the <hi>Subſtance.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Exaction of Tythes</hi> for the Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall Function of this <hi>Everlaſting Prieſthood,</hi> is an abſolute deniall of <hi>Chriſt come in the fleſh,</hi> and of his <hi>everlaſting Prieſthood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Further, it may be conſidered, concerning thoſe <hi>Tythes</hi> unto <hi>Melcheſedec,</hi> that though they were paid to him, and ſo to the Order whereof Chriſt ſhould be our <hi>High-Prieſt forever,</hi> yet they were a voluntary <hi>gift;</hi> for <hi>Abraham</hi> had no Commandement from God to bind him preciſely to that quantity, though the equity of the gift might be granted, yet a neceſſity of the quantity cannot be enforced, though in equity for his own part he was bound to a <hi>gift,</hi> for his owne diſcharge, yet not of neceſſity to a Tenth, as if hee might not have given more or leſſe, or that the other had a Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to receive it, but the one leſt at liberty to <hi>give,</hi> and the other to receive, for <hi>Melchezedec</hi> would not have received them; which plainly proves, he never <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> them,</hi> but that they were a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Offering,</hi> and for Voluntary Offerings we doe not deny, for if any be pleaſed to give the <hi>Tenth of their endercaſe,</hi> or more then the <hi>Tenth,</hi> they may doe as it ſeemeth good in their eyes: So that if from the gift of <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Melebeſedee,</hi> you will enforce any thing unto that Order, it can be but <hi>free-gift,</hi> which we granted be due, ſo that your Antiquity of <hi>Tythes</hi> to this <hi>Prieſthood</hi> is vaniſhed into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>gift of the People;</hi> and from thence you can onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, That <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> of his owne <hi>free-will</hi> gave the <hi>Tenth,</hi> but not that the <hi>Tenth</hi> was ever commanded or exacted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113342:20"/>
Thus if we grant you, That <hi>Abrahams TYTHES at that time were given to that Order, where of Chriſt is our High-Prieſt ſon ever,</hi> yet you ſee, in ſtead of <hi>gaining,</hi> you have loſt the vantage of your <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and it is tranſacted to <hi>voluntary gift,</hi> ſo that from thence you can never prove other then <hi>voluntary gift to be given to that Order.</hi> But if we compare the place in <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 14. with that of <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. we ſhall find that thoſe <hi>Tythes, this Gift,</hi> was no other then <hi>Melohezedec's</hi> proper goods, which <hi>Abraham</hi> had reſcued from <hi>Chederloamer:</hi> For <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 1. it is ſaid, <hi>For this</hi> Melchezedec <hi>King of</hi> Salem, <hi>Prieſt of the Moſt High God who met</hi> Abraham <hi>returning from the ſlaughter &amp;c.</hi> From whence it is clues, that he who went to meet Abraham, afice his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, was <hi>Melcheſedec,</hi> and that it was the Prieſt of the moſt High God that met him, and that this Prieſt was <hi>King of Salem;</hi> So that <hi>he that went out to meet him, and was this Prieſt, and King, muſt needs be this</hi> Melcheſedec, <hi>and in</hi> verſ. 1. 2. it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid, <hi>That to</hi> Melchezedec, Abraham <hi>offered that tenth, ſo that hee to whom</hi> Abraham <hi>offered his</hi> tenth, <hi>was that</hi> Melchezedec, <hi>and that Melchezedec was that Prieſt, and that Prieſt was that King, and that King he that went out to meet Abraham, to whom Abraham gave a</hi> tenth <hi>of his Spoiles;</hi> now theſe things premiſed, and compared to the place in <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 14. 9, 10, 11. Where it is ſaid, <hi>That</hi> Chederlao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>and the Kings with him, conquered the King of</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <hi>took all the goods of</hi> Sodome, <hi>&amp;c. and</hi> verſ. 15, 16. <hi>Abraham purſued them unto</hi> Hoba, <hi>and brought back all the goods, &amp;c. and</hi> verſ. 17. <hi>The King of</hi> Sodome went ora <hi>to meek him, after his return from the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> &amp;c. and is fire. He gave him Terter of all; and verſ. 21, 22, 23. The <hi>King of</hi> Sodom <hi>ſaid</hi> unto Abram, Groe we the Parſons; (to wit the Captives) <hi>and take the goods to the ſelf; and</hi> Abram <hi>ſold to the King of</hi> Sodom, <hi>I will not take from a thread even to a ſhot-faichet, and that I will not take any thing that is thine, &amp;c.</hi> From whence it is moſt evident, <hi>That this King of</hi> Sodom, <hi>that was thus plundered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> goods</hi> Abram <hi>reſcared, dire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> went out to meet</hi> Abram, <hi>that this</hi> Melcheredde; <hi>the Prieſt if the Moſt High God; and that the goods that</hi> Abram gave, has Melchezedec's under goods, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> had it then from him from Sodom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Abram would not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> from in third <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſould other, hee would not take any thing that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this <hi>it ſeems, that</hi> Melchezedec's <hi>goods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Tenth of</hi> Abrams <hi>ſpoiler; and thus to this</hi> Melchezedec, <hi>the Prieſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113342:21"/>
of the Moſt High GOD, Abrahrn gave the Tythes of all;</hi> So that here is a vaſt diſproportion betwixt thoſe <hi>Tythes,</hi> and the <hi>Tythes</hi> which you exact; for thoſe were not the <hi>Tenthes</hi> of <hi>Abrahams</hi> encreaſe, but onely a returne of <hi>Melchezedec's</hi> proper goods; which example af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth but a ſandy foundation for your practiſe; your <hi>Ordinanve for Tythes,</hi> that <hi>Roaring-Meg,</hi> muſt be better planted, or elſe you'l miſſle your Marke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sect">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Clergies <hi>HUMANE TITLE,</hi> the Ordinance for TYTHES.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> whether <hi>Prophetticall</hi> or <hi>Apaſtaticall</hi> that ever I read, none are ſo poſitive, none ſo point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blank to the purpoſe, us <hi>thoſe</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> for the <hi>Ordinance for Tythes</hi> is a Text beyond them all, its <hi>Divinity</hi> is Incomprehenſible to them, beyond the <hi>Speare</hi> of their <hi>Sanction:</hi> But not to detract from is PARLIAMENTARY WORTH, I ſhall not adjudge it ſo farre, as wholly to banniſh is <hi>Divinity</hi> the Precincts of the <hi>Bible,</hi> neither may I, or dare I ſo <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> its a <hi>Sunctity,</hi> to equalize it with the <hi>Sacred;</hi> onely I ſhall preſume, (becauſe I would not too much offend my BRETHREN) to ranck be for the preſent amongſt the <hi>Apocryphe Writings,</hi> as <hi>A Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> HISTORY <hi>of</hi> BELL <hi>and the</hi> DRAGON; for greater Honour then this I cannot deem to be within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of its deferts and it is fite the TWO HOUSES ſhould have all due Praiſe and Honors, their Ordinances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all in time.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:113342:21"/>
This might ſerve to Anſwer their Preſumption, and though to little, yet to as good purpoſe as that ORDINANCE it ſelfe; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>plundering Divinity</hi> be moſt Infallible; yet that <hi>Divinity</hi> which is not founded and derivitive from the <hi>Writings</hi> of the PROPHETS and APOSTLES, muſt give up its <hi>Hallowed-Ghoſt,</hi> expire its <hi>Sanctity,</hi> and be content with more inferiour Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch as it ſelf is, even <hi>Carnall</hi> and <hi>Diabollicall,</hi> and may not be admitted in, but utterly abominated from the Verge of TRUE MAGISTERIALL RIGHT, for its <hi>Bounds</hi> is preciſely confmed within the <hi>Sacred Line</hi> of the WORD, deſigning its proper <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentions,</hi> how farre, and beyond which it may not paſſe: So that, whatſoever is <hi>Tranſgreſſant,</hi> that is not <hi>truly</hi> MAGESTERIALL, and cannot in <hi>equity engage</hi> either in <hi>Divine</hi> or <hi>Humane oblige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to intrude upon CHRIST'S PREROGATIVE, to <hi>uſurpe his Royalty,</hi> is beyond the Line and authority of the WORD, and ſo not within the compaſſe of <hi>Mageſteriall Right:</hi> But this <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Tythes</hi> doth ſo; Therefore <hi>not Mageſteriall or binding.</hi> That it doth ſo, I thus Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To reneance any Ordinance of Chriſt for his Church, over which hee is King, Prieſt, and Prophet, and introduce a contrary, is an encroachment upon his Prerogative, an uſurpation of his Royalty: But in the room of Chriſts Ordinance of Contribution, this Act of the Lords and Commons hath introduced another of a contrary nature,</hi> to wit, <hi>Compulſive Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Therefore, this Ordinance for Tythes is no other then an encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon his Royalty,</hi> a deniall of him to be <hi>Law-giver</hi> to his <hi>Church,</hi> and a ſetting the <hi>Parliament</hi> in his ſtead, as if they were ſo many GODS, <hi>coeternall, eſſentiall with the Father,</hi> for that <hi>prerogative,</hi> that <hi>Legiſlative Power,</hi> is onely proper to the <hi>Deity;</hi> when as wee know theſe are but <hi>mortall men,</hi> ſuch as our ſelves; they are but <hi>Powers of this World,</hi> worldly and humane; and ſuch as their <hi>Powers</hi> are, ſuch are their <hi>Ordinances,</hi> ſuch are their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> even <hi>earthly and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane.</hi> So that if you will have <hi>Churches, Ordinances, &amp;c.</hi> by their <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,</hi> they can be but <hi>Politicall Churches, Politicall Ordinances, &amp;c.</hi> not <hi>Spirituall.</hi> Therefore if you will be <hi>Miniſters in that kind,</hi> ſuch as your <hi>Churches and Ordinances are,</hi> ſuch muſt be your <hi>Preachings,</hi> even <hi>Politicall, Occonomicall,</hi> teach the <hi>Husband-man</hi> how to Plow, the <hi>Citizens</hi> how to <hi>Trade,</hi> the <hi>Butchers</hi> how to <hi>kill Calves,</hi> the <hi>Women to waſh their diſhes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113342:22"/>
One Paſſage in this Ordinance I deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be laid to heart of the People, to wit, pag. 5. <hi>And in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> no ſufficient Diſtreſſe can be found, that then the ſaid Juſtices of Peace, or any other Juſtices of Peace in the ſame County is fortfaid, ſhall and man commit all and every ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo refuſing, to the next common Grale of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> County, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in ſafe cuſtody without Beyle or Mainprize, untill be or they reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively ſhall make full ſatisfaction, according to the ſaid Judgement.</hi> Had not ſuch a Paſſage gone under the Title of <hi>The</hi> LORDS <hi>and</hi> COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON'S, who are choſen for the <hi>Weal</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> I ſhould not have judg'd ie an Act of <hi>Huminity,</hi> our rather the reſult of an Hell bred Conſpiracy by the Devill &amp; his Angells, to confound us with their unreaſonable malice; for what greater Act of Inhumanity can there be, then to cuſt a poor man, that hath nothing, into a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtinking Goale, without Bayle or Main-prize, there to lie, for thoſe Cannibal devoting <hi>Church-babbers,</hi> to ceaze upon <hi>(without Redemption)</hi> untill he <hi>have made full ſatisfaction,</hi> when as before he was caſt in, he had nothing to ſatisfy; and this was the firſt Stone theſe <hi>Maſter-Builders</hi> laid in their bleſſed <hi>Reſormation;</hi> This is the Conſcience of our godly <hi>Divines,</hi> even to ſwallow us up quick, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Goods and all. But I commend the <hi>Impropriators</hi> of the Two Houſes, for their godly Providence over themſelves, and the weal of the People: Yet I am afraid, their wit and Pollicy in this, out-ſtript their honeſty.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 2. line 3. for both in Perſon, r. Both, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Perſon p. o. l. 31. for Religion in them, r. Religion in thoſe Directions. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. for Ordinance for the Supper, r. Ordinance for Ordination of Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
